less and celebrate with song the Lord of Spirits,
1st denoc, chapter 48, verses 4 through 5.
The modern world doesn't acknowledge,
but is nevertheless haunted by spirits, angels, demons,
and saints.
In our time, many year into break free
of the prison of a flat, secular materialism
to see and to know reality as it truly is.
What is this spiritual reality like?
How do we engage with it well?
How do we permeate every day?
life with spiritual presence. Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew
Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung host this live Colin show focused on
enchantment in creation, the union of the scene and unseen as made by God and
experienced by mankind throughout history. Welcome to the Lord of Spirits. Good
evening everyone. Yes, that little voice that you heard over the voiceover was
in fact, Father Stephen, talking over the voice of Sly-
My-
Mike was on? Your mic was on. Oh, I was just answering a question. Oh, not a question
from a listener. I'm sure it was just your plumber or whatever, but while they might be listening
now, I don't know. It's possible. Yeah. Hey, everybody. You're listening to Lord of
Spirits podcast. My coast, whom you just heard, the very Reverend Dr. Stephen D. Young is
with me from Lafayette, Louisiana. And I am in Emmaus, Pennsylvania. And we are live.
if you are the
to us live. You can call us at 855-237-2346 and you can talk to us. And we're going to get your
calls in the second half of the show and our very own beloved, Matyska Trudy, will be taking those
calls. So we stood up a lot of thoughts last time. Probably one or two feelings with our episode
introducing the Torah and especially talking about how it's situated within the Christian church.
And that's evident by the many emails and questions.
we got in our Facebook group.
You got emails in the Facebook group?
Oh yeah.
Yeah, you can email the Facebooks now.
Did you know that?
No, I did not know that.
It's totally a thing.
I issue the Facebooks.
That episode we first talked about how the Torah has not been abolished but fulfilled.
Then we talked about two core Torah principles.
Easy for me to say.
Core Torah, Torah, Torah, Torah, Torah principles.
And those are dwelling safely with God.
and also managing the problem of sin,
including how those principles get worked out in the church.
Now that Christ has come.
So this time, we're gonna continue talking
about these Torah themes,
how the commandments of the Torah continue to be applied
because it was not abolished,
and we're gonna look at three more major themes this time.
Number one, what is clean and unclean?
Number two, how worship works in number three,
probably the most controversial one of them all,
the Torah death penalty.
Dun dun dun dun.
So father is asleep.
say that here in 21st century America we should not be stoning every kid who talks back to his mom.
Yes, because the stoning was we're talking back to your father. Oh,
say man, you're much better than the law. You're a way better Pharisee than I am.
What do you mean by talk? What do you mean by father?
Um, right.
So clean and unclean.
That's that's the already you're jumping all the way ahead to I know, you know,
to the third half with this whole death penalty thing.
I know.
I like spoilers.
We'll get there.
We'll get them.
Tires.
Patients.
Trying to cultivate patients in our listeners since we don't get to the point until like three hours in.
And here you go, jumping the gun, setting a bad example.
4-shame.
the tour will allow me to repent though. So yes, there you go again. That almost constitutes
a lack of repentance if you keep doing it. So you're high handed co-host. So we're starting
out talking about yeah talking about clean and unclean and this may
be the element or theme in the Torah that would be most widely regarded as
able to be disregarded by contemporary people who identify with Christians as
Christians in the United States.
especially when it comes to cleaning uncleaned food animals.
clean and unclean as it relates to bodily functions and fluids clean and unclean as it relates to
just about anything else touching holy things. So I was gonna say I think it feels like a foreign
concept like it seems arbitrary I think to a lot of people like this is clean this is unclean.
Yeah, why you know so what do we really do that? No, we don't. Yeah
resistive rules, you know, complex procedures for getting rid of like yeast and mildew and things.
Right. Not that battles with mildew are not a whole thing in Southern Louisiana, but
the particular religious procedures are less of a thing in Louisiana currently for most people.
I don't know about the local Jewish community. I would have to ask them. But yeah, and so
So since people are not in the habit.
of checking to see Christian people are not in the habit of checking to see if their food is kosher
or not in the habit of worrying about you know petting their dog. In fact you know there's people
who feed their dogs off their own fork. I've seen this. I've seen this. I've not done this.
Right. Even though we now understand the
the term theory of disease.
We still don't attach any religious or moral freight to that kind of thing.
Right.
We, you know, yeah, that's kind of gross.
And yeah, probably shouldn't do that.
Yes, employees must wash their hands before returning to work.
But like, that's not because religion anymore.
Because germs.
But there
There is something very important going on in the Torah in regard to these distinctions
that are made between clean and unclean.
And the point being made with those distinctions is one that's very much still important,
as we will see.
And it's important, I keep using the word important, it's crucial.
The fact that you're in England.
style. Yeah, when we look at, uh,
Grammarly blown up with a little the Soros bubble, right? Um,
that we, we look at what the Torah actually says about this.
Right, because especially again with Leviticus, I think when people think about this,
they're just thinking of, okay, well, there's this big long list of unclean animals,
and then a big long list of clean animals.
and there's a big long list.
of things that make you unclean, right? It's just these lists, right? But there's more to it
than that if you actually read what the Torah says. So for example, in Leviticus 20 verse 25
and this is an important, Locustus, this is in the midst of the food laws.
Right? And this sort of thing, it frames this in an important way.
Yeah, so this is what the verse actually says.
You shall therefore separate the clean beast from the unclean and the unclean bird from
the clean.
You shall not make yourselves detestable by beast or by bird or by anything with which
the ground crawls, which I have set apart for you to hold unclean.
So part of what's going on in designating certain animals clean and certain animals unclean,
and all of the other things that it does.
is unclean. According to this text is that God is teaching the Israelite people, later
the Jewish people, to discern between, to distinguish between clean and unclean. He
is making this a category because the category, the principle involved.
is going to have applications beyond just,
hey, you're unclean after you relieve yourself.
Hey, you're, this animal is unclean and you shouldn't eat it.
Right? You shouldn't eat a vulture. Right?
Or an owl. Beyond that, there is further application of this
principle of clean and unclean. Right?
Alright, and...
God is here giving the Israelites a very practical, a very hands-on, a very literal version
of this.
So that by observing and performing this literal version of separating a clean bird from
an unclean bird. They will also learn on a moral level.
a spiritual level, what is clean and what is unclean, and separate those as well. And when we say that,
this isn't like spiritualizing in the Wu-Wu sense, right? This isn't allegorical interpretation or
application. Yeah, which the idea that like, okay, well now that you've got sort of the point,
don't worry about doing the actual thing.
Right. Right. This is the point that's being made in and through those literal
observances. Yeah. Right. In and through this point, this understanding is being
cultivated. Right. In a very practical way. If you want to hear allegory on this, go
Check out Charles Haddon's Spurgeons, sermon on the owl, the night hawk, and the sparrow.
Who?
Of these birds you shall not eat.
That could be the title of a novel, though.
It is very long and he heads up through a lot of shakainery getting to preaching what
he understands to be the gospel at the end.
You gotta do a lot of-
your domain, right, with, well, the owl represents this, the
night hawk represents this, the sparrow represents that, right?
That's allegory, right? But pointing out that distinguishing
between clean and unclean and practical everyday matters,
right, making that distinction and having that distinction be
part of your thought process, part of your phronoma, right?
part of your right that then is going to apply itself.
to weightier matters. Right? And we're going to go into this now and and describe this more, right?
Because it's important that another piece of this that's critical is that those lists, we already
saw the purpose statement, but those lists are not just arbitrary. Yeah, right. Right. God didn't just
randomly select select
Some animals to say it's okay to eat, and that randomly selects some other animals and
say, no, not these.
Yeah, so when they received a list, they would have said, oh, we see what he's doing here.
Right.
And he's not, didn't randomly select some bodily functions that make you unclean and then
some other ones are fine.
Right.
None of this is sort of arbitrary, right?
Or random or just God's fiat.
There is, first of all, something real here
and then something that's being communicated
about that reality.
So why are things unclean?
Right, that's the question we really need to ask
because of course, when God creates everything
in Genesis 1, right, He says after each day of creation,
He calls it Tofe in Hebrew.
He says it's good, it's beautiful.
Yeah, it doesn't say.
and on the fifth day God made unclean stuff. Yeah, yeah, he doesn't get to the end and say,
yeah, it's kind of filthy, right? It's now that I made everything, you know, these things are clean.
Like, that's not, that's not Adam and Eve are not presented with clean and unclean animals.
Yeah. So what needs to come in dust in the air, right? That's not a thing, right?
But there's this transition in Genesis 3 when the curve
verse is an unseated. Right? Now, I think we talked about this back in the
blessing in cursus episode, but it bears repeating. Sometimes people read this
as God cursing Adam and then cursing Eve and then cursing the devil. Right? And
that's not the way it's actually presented in the text. Right? The way it's
presented in the text is...
God is describing the curse.
He is describing the cursed state of the world now as a result of the actions of Adam and Eve and the devil.
Yeah, they
Taint in the world.
Right. This is the consequence. And it's kind of summed up in what he says to Adam.
Cursed is the ground because of you.
Right.
God doesn't say curse.
you Adam, I'm going to make your life difficult.
Right.
Curse you Adam.
Sorry.
He says, right, uh, the ground is now cursed, the earth, literally, the land, right,
the earth, the creation is now under in this state of curse because of what you have
done.
Right.
which is as we've...
said before a number of times that I showed the opposite of what he was supposed to do.
He and Eve were supposed to go out from Eden and put the world in order and fill it with
life until the whole world was Eden.
And what he has done is had the opposite effect.
Right?
The creation he was put in charge of, the creation he was to tend like a garden he has now
corrupted.
is now tainted.
And so this is the state of the world from that on in the Hebrew scriptures in the Old Testament.
By the time we get to the flood, the whole world, the curse is at the point where everyone's thoughts are always evil all the time.
It's gotten as bad as it can get.
And so God uncreates everything and purifies it with water.
right and then creates again. Yeah. And then as we've talked about before, things
immediately start to run in the same direction. Dimmerod shows up, right, we got
Neffellum coming back. Tower of Babel happens. Semiramis. And God rather than
destroying the world again, which you promise he wouldn't do, he steps back away.
but that leaves the world in this state of...
curse. When God then approaches humanity again beginning with Abraham, but then especially
with the giving of the Torah at Mount Sinai, God is essentially establishing an island or
an outpost in the midst of a cursed world. So you know, you could say this about Abraham
in his family, wherever they're traveling as nomads.
Alright?
but especially once we have the Torah being given, and like we talked about last time,
God is going to come and dwell among his people, and so there have to be these concentric circles
of holiness, of purity, of cleanness, but even the farthest out concentric circle, which is just
the borders of the Israelite camp, the wilderness, or the borders of Israel slash you.
right once they're there in the land. That furthest boundary is still maintaining a level of purity
and holiness higher than the rest of the world. Yeah, yeah, so I mean it's like, you know, the flood
comes and there is a boundary that's set up which is the arc, right? And the people and
people and animals in it are saved.
And then when the flood is over, it's not like
like, okay, everything is great now because the demonic force of sin is still at loose in
the world.
Right.
Is that right away with ham, who's like cane?
Yeah.
And so, I mean, a way to picture this, right, is, you know, you've got the whole world covered
in darkness except for this one little island of light.
Right.
And holiness.
through the history of Israel in the
scriptures that lights minimally flickering. Yeah, right. Right. And perpetually looking ready to go
out. Right. There's this little island. And so there has to be, right, to keep that light going,
that purie going, there has to be this level of purity maintained. And we talked last time about
how there's moral and ceremonial
uncleanness, moral and ceremonial impurity. And we talked about how ceremonial impurity
is not necessarily a moral issue. Right. So using the restroom is not immoral. Right.
be more controversial.
Shelley, women menstruating is not immoral.
Right. Right.
Having a wound that bleeds is not a moral. Right.
None of these things are immoral, but they do make you unclean
Right in a very practical literal way
Yeah, right you need to clean yourself afterwards
Moral impurity also makes you ceremonially impure
right, right? Because the sin not only is a sin that does damage to you, to whoever
else was involved, whatever injured party there might be, but that sin leaves this
taint, this stain. Yeah, and I think it's, it's good to underline as well that it's not
just a matter of defining things as clean and unclean, and you know, this is how you wash up
but whatever.
But it's so that, and we talked about this last time,
but it's so that people can approach God's dwelling place
and not be destroyed.
Right? So it's cleaning up for a purpose.
It's not like just saying this thing is good
and this is bad.
You know, it's not that.
It has a purpose behind it,
as in the idea is to be able to commune with God.
You know, just like, you know,
Watch your hands before you come to the-
table kids, right? And those very literal things, right? If you understand it, you
internalize those very literal things, they will help you understand the idea of moral
impurity, right? Right. Right. They'll help you understand what it means to have a stain,
Right? A moral stain on your life. Right?
And so these ideas...
work together. But what doesn't happen when the Torah is given is the nature of Israel is not made
perfect. All at once, all of the people, the people still sin. And the people still do things that
cause them to contract ceremonial uncleanness. And the fact that that keeps happening, the fact that
living life in a sinful world, what we would call a fallen world.
Right?
Causes them to become physically impure and needed to be clean is again supposed to be
a pointer to help them internalize the fact that in addition to that, living in a fallen
world often forces people to make compromises and do things that compromise them morally.
even when not forced we make a lot of un...
forced errors. Right. We also just have our own evil motives and do evil things. Right.
But even if we're trying, right, the world we live in is a simple reality that sometimes
we find ourselves in situations in this world where there is no good option. There are
better and worse options. But there is no good
good one. Right, there is no good one. For example, there are times when people or groups
of people are forced to resort to violence because the consequences of not doing it are far
worse. Yeah, that doesn't make the violence good or justified or right. Right. And anyone
who's had to perform acts of violence in that kind of situation can tell you for sure
there.
experience that there was nothing good about it, but it was what had to be done.
Right. And the Torah takes this into account. For example, someone comes back from war, even if it
is a war that was completely allowable by the Torah that followed all the commandments in
Deuteronomy 10 about warfare perfectly. The returning soldiers have this whole period of penance
at the edge of the camp where they cleaned the blood off their weapons.
off of themselves. They spent time there repenting before they reintegrated into the people.
There was a way of dealing with this. And so that means in order, if we're talking about our
island of light again, in order for that thing to continue to exist, there has to be ongoing purification
and forgiveness.
going on to allow that level of holiness and purity to exist because the people are not
capable of maintaining it by their own efforts, by just not sinning or not contracting unclean
this. They are going to do both. And so there has to be a process for dealing with it.
Take care of it.
This is sort of the point where the two things we talked about.
last week meet. We talked about the concentric circles of holiness, right, and we talked about
purification and the management of sin. This is the place where those things meet, right,
practically, right, is that having those concentric circles of holiness requires the management of sin.
Right, the two go together.
And so the most sort of immediate way of dealing with uncleanness is through ceremonial
washings.
And we talked about this a little I know in our baptism episode.
But the even ceremonial impurity, if it wasn't dealt with properly, could turn into moral
impurity. Good turn.
into an issue of sin. Right? If those procedures were dealing with it, we're not followed. And we get
some of this in Numbers chapter 19. Yeah, so there's, I mean, the whole chapters were
reading. Obviously, any chapter in the scriptures were, but anyway, we're going to just read a couple
of verses from that. There's a couple of same ones, but I won't say what book. Just say some chapters
will probably be less immediately edifying than others.
Yeah, okay. So verse 13 of Numbers 19, whoever touches a dead person, the body of anyone
who has died and does not cleanse himself defiles the tabernacle of the Lord, and that
person shall be cut off from Israel because the water for impurity was not thrown on him.
He shall be unclean. His uncleanness is still on him. And then similarly, verse 20, if
The man who is unclean does not cleanse himself.
That person shall be cut off from the midst of the assembly since he has defiled the sanctuary of the Lord
Because the water for impurity has not been thrown on him. He is unclean
So this is not just someone who's unclean. This is someone who does not wash himself and therefore chooses to remain unclean
Right, and I love that translation of the water of impurity being thrown on him
Like some priest would come running up with a bucket full of water and just
just chuck it at you.
Which I mean...
You know, the immediate image that came to my mind was at the end of a sports ball game,
you know, when members of the team go and and ritually cleanse the coach with the
Gatorade. Yeah. Yeah. It's got what plants crave electrolytes. Um, so, uh, yeah, but
notice here, in verse 13, the father Andrew red, it's about talking about somebody who
touches a dead person, the body of anyone who has died. There is nothing sinful about
Right.
I mean, bearing a dead person is a good work.
Baring a dead person with no family is a good work.
And of course, you're expected.
It's a duty for you to bury your father.
Oh, yeah.
Bury your mother, right?
To bury family members in an appropriate way, right?
So, that's not a sinful thing to do, right, to bury someone.
you could track ceremonial uncleanness.
A dead body is unclean.
And so if a person refuses to tend to properly cleanse themselves and tries to return to
regular life, then in verse 20 is even more general.
Right.
And notice it says, we'll come back to this in the third half, but they'll be cut off
from the bits of the assembly.
This is like the death penalty for not washing up after you use the bathroom.
That's literally what it says.
Right.
Like, we got to start with what it actually says.
We're going to keep talking about it, but that is what it says.
Right.
Yeah.
Um, notice also here, because this is about to become important.
Notice how it says that in verse 13, it says that that person has defiled the tabernacle.
In verse 20 it says he is defiled the sanctuary, the holy place.
Okay. This isn't just talking about priests. Yeah. Priests are the only ones who went in there.
So this person may not have gone anywhere near the tabernacle proper, right?
But he is still defiled it. He may not have gone anywhere near the holy place, but he's still defiled it
by his self.
So this is part of what we were talking about last time and that we're about to talk about
some more, right?
That the sanctuary, that inner circle, the most holy place, the holy place, right?
The tabernacle.
This is the holiest part of the concentric circle.
So this is the place where sin is the most dangerous, right?
But here we see this principle that is in the Torah that...
even if
That even Israelites sin that is performed
Outside the tabernacle outside the camp even
Still can potentially bring this taint of curse to the tabernacle where it is most dangerous
And so this is the reason
Where we're going to talk about more but this is the reason for that cut off from among the people language
It's not just, oh, he might experience death by holiness even though he's not actually going into the holy place. It's
He the whole camp might experience death by holiness
Because of what he's done
Hmm
And let me tell you if you really want to get into this stuff as I have you will find a rich and fascinating
scholarly literature about how the taint of sin gets from the sitting Israelite to the sanctuary
Oh, like if it sort of physically moves there or appears there or how exactly that works because
people need to write journal articles at dissertations, right?
But suffice for tonight, we won't go into all that.
Suffice for tonight, it does.
Right.
What they do, even away from the sanctuary affects the purity of the sanctuary of the place
This word God is dwelling.
because he is dwelling with them, even if they're not walking in physically.
Right? So there is this great danger, not only for the person who becomes ceremonially
unclean and doesn't deal with it appropriately, but for the whole people because of his disobedience.
I think I could use his instead of his or her because we're talking about bad things, right?
Um, no, he's gonna be like, you need to denounce simple women also.
Um, but, uh, well, maybe somebody, well, but, um, and so we have to have, we have to
have a very established system for how to deal with this to prevent that danger.
Right.
And so we have this procedure that's slightly different depending on who it is.
But the first
thing when someone sins is what we would now call from the Latin penance, but what we
mean by that is restitution, restoration.
Yeah, make it make it right.
Fix it.
Fix the thing that you broke, which is which that's the actions that constitute repentance.
Right.
Not feeling bad about it.
Not wanting to avoid the consequences of your actions.
Yeah, and and and not just merely stopping doing bad stuff.
Yes.
obviously you
can't repent if you don't stop doing bad stuff.
Yes.
Don't steal from anybody else,
but you also need to pay back what you stole from the first guy.
Right.
So you do that.
And then typically, right, you offer a sacrifice.
Now, when we say offer sacrifice, that's not literal under the Torah,
because the you is probably not a priest.
Right.
Sacrifices.
brought for what you did to the tabernacle where it is sacrificed. Right. And then once
that is taken care of, once the moral issue is taken care of, then there is ceremonial
washing. If you're a priest to sins, this gets changed up a little bit because of course
for you to go and offer a sacrifice for yourself, you have to wash first.
Yeah, because the priest is going in.
into the tabernacle. Right. Right. So that gets inverted. Because no one else,
just as a reminder, everybody, no one else goes into the tabernacle, that area, except for
the priests. Yes. We cannot, we cannot stress this enough. Because, you know, just wait
for a worship debate to come up. Right. And you're going to have someone say, we'll look
they used music.
physical instruments in temple worship, right? And when someone makes that argument, they're
sort of an unspoken presupposition that like what used to happen in ancient Israel is
that of the Sabbath day, everybody would trek over to the temple in Jerusalem and they'd
all go worship God there. Like they'd all file in and have a worship service where they
use musical instruments. That never happened. Right. So even if they were, even if they were
using
musical instruments in the temple, like some of these people say that they were, that was
not something that most people would have ever seen or heard.
Yes.
That would have been something accompanying the priests on duty going about and fulfilling
their duties with some kind of music in the background.
Like the Psalms of Ascent are called the Psalms of Ascent not because...
These are the Psalms they sang in the worship service at the temple.
It's these those were the Psalms that people sang on their way making the hike to Jerusalem
for the feasts when they were able to right and it took a long time but they would they
got there they didn't go in.
Yeah, they would stand at the door hand over their animals to the priests.
Yeah, so...
We have to really emphasize this, right?
Because we've projected our modern worship services,
or at best, projected like a Jewish synagogue service back into the temple.
And synagogue worship and temple worship were two very different things
when temples and synagogues coexisted.
Yeah.
There were very strict rules.
There were all kinds of temple things you weren't allowed to do in the synagogue.
Thank you.
Right. And, you know, I have had someone Jewish who went to an orthodox service say to
me, where do you guys get off doing XYZ? You're only allowed to do that at the temple.
We'll get to more of that in a second and a half. But these were very, very, very different
things. But so this brings us to the day of atonement.
the annual day of a
is really for dealing with this issue.
Dealing with the danger that the sins of the people
create in those sins, defiling the sanctuary,
even if they aren't committed there.
And the threat to the entire community of death
by holiness that that presents.
This is why we need to have an annual day of atonement
in the Torah.
And if you read Leviticus chapter 16 closely,
being closely, which is where the day...
a tonement is laid out. What you find is that a tonement is not made for people.
Yep. A tonement is made for the physical accoutreement of the tabernacle and the later temple.
It's about the space. Yeah. That is the language, a tone for the altar, a tone for the arc of
the covenant. A tone for the table. A tone for the table.
the ultra Vincent, right? You're atoning for physical objects.
Yeah. Now you're atoning because of what people did to those objects.
Effective. Well, they they people did nowhere near those objects.
Yeah. Yeah. There's sort of the taint. Right. It doesn't presuppose that someone pulled an
antichypiphanies and went in there and defiled the altar. Yeah. Sure. Sure. Yeah. So it could be
It could be direct, but probably indirect.
99% of the time it was indirect.
Right.
Yeah.
Neh Da Bina Buhu.
That was direct.
There are incidents.
There are many incidents.
Right.
But 99.9% of the time, you know, most years they were not, you know, atoning for that.
But they're atoning for these objects.
Let me suggest this ought to condition how we understand the meaning of the word make
atonement.
Right.
If your definition of this is
what atonement is makes no sense.
When you say make atonement for the alter
or make atonement for the arc of the covenant,
you have misunderstood make atonement.
I'll put a finer point on it, okay.
They did not punish a goat for the sins of the table.
Yeah.
Well, I think, you know, like the way that atonement
often gets used in a lot of discourse,
especially post-reformation,
is essentially as the
So it were some kind of synonym for the Western Christian doctrine of satisfaction.
Right?
That, that, and so obviously it would only apply to humans because what did it a table
ever do to God?
Right.
You know, so, but, but clearly when you look at Levicus and when it talks about the David
to him and it's not talking about paying off a person's sins.
It's about
cleaning up a space. Right. Right. It's not about turning away God's wrath in the sense of God is really
angry, but he'll take some goat blood instead of yours. Yeah. God's going to smite the altar because
no, wait, that's not what's going to happen. Yeah. It's not the blood for the blood God thing. It's
right. Yeah. It's God's wrath in the sense of death by holiness. In the sense of there is this
danger of sinful
humanity beginning with sinful Israel being consumed by God's holiness. If their sin isn't
what? Isn't what? Because notice this isn't about God punishing the sin. This is about them being
consumed in their sin. So what needs to happen to that sin? Well, what happens in Leviticus 16
the day of Atonement, Ritual.
Step 1
The sin is taken away.
Right, there's the goat for his asal.
The sins of the people
Right are taking a put on this goat
Which then isn't killed and isn't sacrificed you can't sacrifice it because it's now unclean
Full of sins
Remember sacrifice is a shared meal with your God you would not offer
offer. You cannot offer unclean animals.
as sacrifices. Yeah. That's like rule one of unclean animals. Offer he wanted to
God as a sacrifice is way worse than just eating it. Yeah. Right. So that's right out. And
it's sent right out into the wilderness. So that goat is called the goat for his nasal.
Yeah, the goat for his asal. There are a lot of folks now who, especially because they don't like so much,
quote unquote supernatural in their Bible, want to read a zazel very literally because azzles a goat.
Right. So a zazel can literally mean the goat that goes away. This is where scapegoat comes from.
Yeah, as they were, scape is in escap, is in go away, right?
So I say, oh, it just means the goat that goes away.
There's something much deeper going on here.
And this isn't just because a Zazel becomes this demonic figure in some later Jewish literature,
which he does.
But this is also built into the Torah because, guess what comes after Leviticus 16?
Leviticus 17.
Yes.
But wait, there's more Leviticus 17.
There is verse 7.
Yeah.
which says this, so they shall no more sacrifice their sacrifices to goat demons
after whom they whore. This shall be a statute forever for them throughout their generations.
So it's flipping it on its head in a sense, right? So like, don't sacrifice to goat demons.
Instead, we're going to be using this goat, which is not a demon. It's a goat, like a goat.
and we're going to put the Sins on it and send it out into the
wilderness so that a zeal can basically wreak the goat demon can reclaim what belongs to him,
which is the sin. So the goat is being as a vehicle. You're taking that sin and saying return
to sender. Yeah. Now it's not being sacrificed to a zeal. That would mean a ritual offering
and eating together with a zeal. Like that's the whole point is you're not doing that. Right.
The note is not killed.
in Leviticus 16. Yeah, not put on the barbecue. It's not it is it's not
increments. It is true that a practice developed later. Once they'd lead the
go down, they push it off a cliff. Kill it. Right. But that's not part of the
ritual in the actual scriptures. Yeah. Right. So all of our Protestant friends
especially should put no stock in that. Yeah. Because it's not in the Bible.
It's an extra biblical tradition. You guys don't like
those. There you go. And reminder, I mean, sacrifice is not the thing that makes sacrifice,
sacrifice is not the killing. Right. It's the offering on an altar and shared eating or
whole burnt offering, you know, on the altar. It's not the killing. And they shoved an
off a cliff for a very practical reason to stop it from wandering back into town. Yeah. Yeah.
Don't don't bring the sins back. Right. That's awkward. Right. You know, you just got rid of all
your sins on this go no wait he just showed up at Bob's house right what do we do now
Well, we did back out there, I guess.
So don't touch it.
So that's why they started pushing it off a cliff.
Now in just a second, we're going to talk about why that particular mode of death showed up later.
Right. But so this procedure for atonement had to be repeated every year.
Right.
because every year people kept sinning.
And while the forgiveness of sins was happening through the daily sin offerings, remember,
this is additional.
There are daily sin offerings going on.
People are making sin offerings, repenting of their sins, taking care of it.
But there's still this taint that's developing in and around the sanctuary, the stain of
sin, this curse, right?
This uncleanness, this impurity that has to be dealt with, that has to be purified.
And every year, this has to be done.
every year this has.
to be done over and over and over again, just to keep this little island. Right. Let alone
the rest of the world. And once we get into the second temple period and Jewish people
understood this, they began to see in terms of their eschatology, in terms of their thinking
about the end, the future, right? And the end of this world, that this problem...
of the world being under a curse.
There's wickedness.
And of this constant purification being needed just for this little island, God was going
to deal with this problem, sort of once and for all, with some kind of finality in the
future.
There was going to be some kind of eschatological day of atonement that was going to happen in
the future.
And we see related ideas to this expressed in a whole
a bunch of places in second-templed Jewish literature.
Right, and this idea that there's going to come a day,
there's going to come a point when God is going to deal with
Azazel himself.
Not just keep shipping the sin back to him, but actually deal
with this guy. And deal with the sin and deal with the curse
once and for all, not only in the little island, deal with it
once and for all, so we don't need to keep doing this
every year.
deal with it for the whole world, right? Turn the whole world into that island. Expand that out to
include the whole creation. And this eschatological day of atonement gets imagined in different ways
in the details, but even some of the details are the same. So one of the details is that this
This is Azulfella is going to get us come up
And that's going to come in the form of him being bound him being chained up
And thrown into a pit in the earth
That's the sort of form this is going to take
I feel like I've seen that in an icon somewhere. Yeah, and
This is where the idea of pushing the goat off a cliff comes from I mean, there's a lot of easier ways to kill a goat
right you just let it throw
use an axe, you can write, but leading it to a cliff and pushing it off is kind of
an inefficient way. But this idea of throwing it into a crag in the earth to a
Zazel comes from this idea. Right. And so that added traditional element that
develops in the second temple period develops related to this tradition. It's
an element that looks forward to that ultimate eschatological day of
of atonement. When the world will be purified from Azazel.
And it works.
Right. So in first,
in the book of Enoch,
which I know is all we talk about on this show every.
We really should do a show on Enoch.
Yes. Or two.
Yeah.
I mean, there are several enics to choose from.
I mean, he's my favorite slea stack, first of all.
Um,
but, uh,
no, sorry.
In first day of the book of Enoch,
It's St. Michael the RK.
who comes and sort of whoops up on on as azo at least in what there's also they also be Raphael who
whoops up on which is interesting because Raphael of course is associated with healing in
And in, in, in first scenic, there's, there's a nice little summary verse, right?
That talks about this when they
are being commanded to go take care of Azazel.
Yeah, it says, and the whole earth has been corrupted through the works that were taught
by Azazel to him ascribe all sin.
And it's interesting, it's not just Azazel has corrupted the whole world.
It's that he, that he taught works through which the world was corrupted, which is this
idea of, as we've talked about in the past in this show, of synergizing.
with demons that when we sin, we bring demonic corruption and energy into the world.
Right.
And then that's what corrupts the whole world is.
The human's cooperating with demonic power.
And so here, that's why this is sort of eschatological and final all the sin in the world now is
he's balled up and thrown onto a zazel.
Right.
And all the corruption.
Right, that it caused. That's first in a 10-8, by the way.
In the apocalypse of Abraham, which is another one of these texts, there's a
being who is the angel of the Lord. Right. His name is Yehoel, which is a
combination of a typical angel name that ends in L, the name Yahweh. So the name of
of this angel is you.
Yahweh God. And we need to understand what's going on in naming an angel that in the sense
that the angel of the Lord, remember an Exodus, Moses is told that there's going to be this angel
who will go before them and that God says he will put his name in him. So this very, this
literalizes that to the extreme. Yes. So this is trying to convey, this isn't just an angel,
This is just one of the archangels. This is the angel of the Lord.
Right, and he shows up dressed as a priest to
officiate and lead Abraham in this
Eschatological Day of Atonement against Azazal
in the Apocalypse of Abraham
Okay, so this is sort of a well-testified
to tradition
and
I'll just come out and say it so when you get to
first John, the first epistle of St. John, which is if we're talking about using the word
elisterio, elisterio. And if we're talking about using the words, the Greek vocabulary related
to atonement, even though it's a relatively short letter, it uses that vocabulary more than
any other book of the New Testament.
Right, so a lot of people they're doing their atonement theories.
pulling this in that verse from St. Paul here and there saying it's about atonement.
Okay, whatever. First John is actually talking about atonement using the words, right? And
he, St. John, very clearly, I mean, obviously we've talked about the binding of the devil
and revelation before on the show. There's a clue connection here to the binding of his nasal,
Right, like obviously.
and also St. Matthew's Gospel, which is another look at the New Testament that relies a lot on
the Innocic traditions. We have the binding of the strong man. But in 1 John, he says things like,
for example, that the son of God came, the Messiah, Jesus, came to destroy the works of the evil one.
Not to destroy the evil one or defeat the evil one to destroy the works of the evil one.
Sounds a lot like Verstienic 10-8.
Yeah, yeah.
Right.
And he says that in his discussion of Christ's atonement.
About that.
And to put a fine point on it, right?
First John 2 verse 2, right, Christ came to make a tone.
not only for our sins, but also for the whole world.
Right? This is one of our themes on the show whenever we talk about atonement, Christ is both goats, right?
So Christ atones for our sin, he takes away our sin,
right? But then he also atones for the whole world.
And and just as a side note, everybody, if you're new to the podcast or new where one of our older episodes
It's called the priest shall make it
and the whole episode is about the day of Atonement.
So if it feels like we're not covering everything,
it's because we did before.
Yes.
And so this is a more pointed discussion.
Yeah.
But so when St. John says, and for the whole world,
he means the whole physical, material world,
which has now been purified by Christ's blood
like the sanctuary, the whole creation.
And all the sin has been taken.
away. And we see in the New Testament the immediate effects of this. We see the
immediate effects of this in, for example, the acts of the apostles.
People are now able to have, as we talked about last time, the Holy Spirit come
and dwell within them, like the sanctuary, because they've been purified with Christ.
blood and because their sin has been taken away. We see with St. Peter going to Cornelius
and the vision he has before Cornelius, that Cornelius quad Gentile, animals,
quaw created things are not ceremonially unclean in and of themselves anymore.
Nothing is in clean of itself
But right but
I know where some folks listening to this are going
You're trying to get rid of that difference between abolished and fulfilled again, right?
You're trying to go down this road of right well, okay, so we don't have to worry about cleaning and unclean anymore because everything's clean
right
Yeah, I don't have to wash my hair
when I leave the bathroom anymore because see that makes no sense. Right? That's right.
And obviously, there's still moral uncleanness in the world. Right. Right. So obviously, that's not
what that means. Right. So there's been a change. But the New Testament tells us more than that
in describing that change. Now we're going to look at some...
verses from Saint Paul that address this very directly using the language of clean and
unclean.
Yeah.
Okay.
So in Romans chapter 14, verse 14, Saint Paul says, I know and then persuaded in the Lord
Jesus that nothing is unclean in itself, but it is unclean for anyone who thinks it unclean.
He doesn't, he's not saying like, what is it, Hamlet, you know?
Nothing is good or bad, but thinking makes it so.
Yeah.
That's not what he means.
If I think someone is filthy, then they're filthy in need of it.
So the power of negative thinking.
Yeah.
Right.
No, this is that it is not, nothing is innately unclean.
But it could become unclean based on how we treat it and how we use it and what we do with
it.
Right.
So St. Paul will set up on one hand, receiving things with prayer and thanksgiving to God.
Right, as the proper way to receive any
created thing that comes into our life, right, or person, right?
But there's a lot of other things you can do as we all know, right?
You could take food and you could offer it to an idol, right?
There was there was nothing innately, you know,
impure or unclean about that lamb or that goat.
But now you've taken in, you've done something unclean and impure with it.
Well,
I mean, this is the reason we get our houses blessed, right?
Or anything blessed.
It's not because it's unclean and none of itself, right?
It's that we have sinned.
Yes.
You know, and it's no longer trying to maintain this island
of cleanliness and the midst of an unclean world in general,
but rather that the world has been cleaned by the work of Christ.
But we can still mess it up by our own sense.
And so there needs to be this, this, so it's, it's similar in certain ways to the,
the old system of sin management, but in, and pretty significant ways, it's,
it's different as well. Right. There are continuities at this continuity.
There we go. That could be it. But yeah, right there, there is no, you know,
your body and no part of your body is innately unclear.
but you could take your body and do unclean and impure things with it.
Obviously.
So he says that in Romans.
Now we're going to look at a little different angle.
Something he says in 1 Corinthians.
Yeah.
So this is 1 Corinthians chapter 7 verse 14.
St. Paul says,
says, for the unbelieving husband is made holy because of his wife.
And the unbelief-
wife is made holy because of her husband. Otherwise, your children would be unclean. But as it is,
they are holy. Right. So what's going on here? He's talking about
families in which one spouse, and we're talking, we're ready to Corinth. So this is mostly former pagans.
Right. Where one spouse is still a pagan and the other has become a Christian.
Right.
And in the context of this, St. Paul has urged very strongly that if it all possible, those
couples should not separate or get divorced.
Yeah.
Right, but they should stay together.
Now, this is not the same as, don't marry a pig.
Right.
He's equally strongly says, do not be, you know, unequally yoked, right?
Don't sign up for this situation because it's very difficult, right?
But if you find yourself in this very difficult situation,
thinking of divorce as an easy answer to it is wrong.
Yeah.
Right.
And that's, of course, mainly directed at men because women were kind of stuck, right?
That's not by, not by Christian design, but by that's because how the world worked in
the first century.
Right.
That's how the Roman Empire was.
Yes.
That's, you know.
So what's the Impaul is doing here?
you know how how does he understand it where he's
able to say like, okay, well somehow, like if the wife is a Christian, that somehow makes her
pagan husband holy. And then her children holy and not unclean. What is that? Like, how does that work?
Right. And if you, if you approach this in a very individualistic way and you're thinking about
holiness, purely in
terms of quote unquote, getting saved. Then this gets really confusing. Because then
it's like, well, wait a minute. This husband is saved, even though he's still a pagan.
Right. Even though he's still communing with deities. Right. And the kids are sort of somehow
automatically saved. You know, I mean, if that were true, we'd have to baptize them. Anyway,
sorry, imaginary interlocutor. The, right. But that of course is a category confusion.
right because clearly you'd what say Paul said.
here the opposite of holy is not unsaved the opposite of holy is unclean so he is making a clean and
unclean distinction right a clean and unclean distinction a pure and impure distinction and he is
basing this on the understanding of circumcision right because in the Jewish world the Torah the way
that you become part of the covenant is by being circumcised if you're male.
Right, but if you're if you're a woman or a daughter a girl
Then you are either the the child the daughter of a circumcised man or the wife of a circumcised man
And so you're included through his circumcision right his circumcision that we've talked about circumcision before on the show
And what it's a sign of but the sign of being separate being
Cut off from the world separate from the world, right that holiness that the circumcision entails
is equally true of the spouse, right, the daughter, even though they're not, you know, Israel
never practice what's called female circumcision, which is a completely different thing.
Yes.
Not even related to male circumcision.
Herendus.
Herific.
Evil.
Right.
So what St. Paul does is he takes that theological understanding and he applies it essentially
de-baptism.
Right.
Uh, essentially de-baptism.
And said is that it because baptism was done to everyone, it wasn't just males who were
baptized.
Right.
It was men, women, children who were baptized.
Um, that even if we're in a situation where the father is a pagan and therefore he won't
allow the children to be baptized, right.
woman who is baptized and who is a Christian, her holiness her being set apart.
from the world, right? She by that sets apart the her whole family, right? It is
sort of communicated, right, that cleanness or that holly is, right? That separation
from the rest of the world, even if the husband in this case, right? And this would go the other
way also, right? Where it would be almost identical to circumcision, where you know, the believing
Father, but in the Roman Empire that was less of
a situation, right, because bluntly in the Roman Empire, if the Potter
familiarist became a Christian, everybody became a Christian in the family.
If you wanted to stay in the family and not die, that's just the way society
worked. But he's extending this, right, this promise to women. And so
got to remember this is the basic building block right the circle.
circumcised male head of family is the basic building block of Israel and of the later Jewish people.
Right. You have a family headed by a circumcised male through circumcised the other males of that household.
Right. Those households make up clans, those clans make up tribes, those tribes make up Israel.
That's the building block.
Right?
And so St. Paul, by saying this about Christian families,
right, these families are the building blocks of the church,
right, of the assembly, right, which is the continuation of the assembly
of the Hebrew Scriptures, the assembly of the Old Testament,
the assembly of Israel.
as it continues to the church, the building block is still.
Right? These believing family units. Right? But so the one believing parent, the one believing family member connects that whole family to the assembly, to the church and its life.
its life. And makes it part of that clean space.
of the world, right, which seems bent on continuing to repelute itself. That's where he's
going with this idea. Yeah. And God willing through that, those other people in the family
will also come closer to Christ and, you know, potentially experience salvation as well.
Right, but remember the salvation that comes in Christ
is not just individual people going to heaven, not hell when they die.
In fact, that's not even what it's about at all, as we've talked about many times of the show.
But this idea of just personal or individual salvation, right?
Otherwise, passages like where St. Paul says,
Christ is the savior of all men, especially those who believe,
or especially those who are faithful, makes no sense.
Yeah, there's especially...
Right. So there are benefits of
Christ salvation, right, that aren't just the kind of personal salvation we think of.
Yeah, right. And these are the kind of benefits that St. Paul is talking about being received by
the other members of the family, even if they are not faithful Christians like the one person who is.
Right. So one more example from St. Paul. Okay. So this is from 2nd Corinthians chapter 6,
for 17. Therefore, go out from their midst.
and be separate from them, says the Lord, and touch no unclean thing, then I will welcome you.
So we see that dynamics up right there, which is approaching God means being clean.
Right.
Gotta be clean first.
And St. Paul is saying this after the death and resurrection of Christ in the coming of the Holy Spirit.
Yeah.
Right.
There's unclean things.
Even then.
The pagan world out there.
Right? Those people are no longer unclean just because they're Gentiles, just because they're
going. Right? That doesn't necessarily make them unclean or impure, but actions they take,
sinful wicked actions they take, pollute them, make them impure. Right? That needs to be purified,
Right? Baptism, right, etc. When they...
come into the church, right? But there is still an inside and outside.
Right. It is not an island in the midst of darkness anymore. Right.
Especially since the church is spread out through the whole world. Right.
But there are still dark places. There are still places where the light is not
shining as brightly yet. Yeah. And one thing I think this would be a good
moment to mention this. We had a number of people asking the last couple of
weeks. Like what does it mean?
mean if that Christ has taken care of the problem of sin once for all. I still see sins in
myself around me. Other people like what he did to care sin, you know, it's lit. You're
supposed to quit that. Yeah. It's not going to happen with the sinning. But this is part
of what that means that there's been a fundamental shift in the environment, so to speak, atonement
for the whole world. Yes, you know, no longer do we live under the
the heavy weight of sin everywhere.
Now it's only present if we bring it in.
We're not trying to defend an outpost of light
in a dark world, we're going out and shining a light
into the dark places that still remain in the world.
Right.
And I think for defense to offense.
Yeah, and part of it is that no one alive knows
what it was like to be alive
when paganism ruled the whole world.
Well, we don't.
We're the same.
Yes, yes, of course you don't I mean yeah, yeah, yeah, I know I'm actually you for no reason. Thank you. It's fine
It's fine. You're pathetic about it. It's okay
Well someone wanted to I'm actually you recently because you use the phrase God can't I think you said God
Nothing God can't
No, that was just I was really angry at a manual can't
Well, there are many good reasons for that.
Yeah.
They've interpreted that.
transcript get it wrong.
They spell can't differently.
But, um, right, that, that Christ dealing with the problem of sin once for all is, is not
that there's no sin left in the world.
That's not what that means.
It means that all sin is now on the run.
And, you know, as we've said many times, now is the time when he rules in the midst of
of his enemies until all his enemies will be put in
his feet. That is in process. You know, a D day has happened to put it in World War II
metaphorical terms. Right. The decisive battle has been won. So he's, it's like you could
say that a D day, you know, the threat of, well, let's be two episodes in Rolemen,
Sean Nazis, the threat of the Nazis was dealt with. What's it for?
Come on. Let's play it out. Talk about pullpons or something. The command rouge. Oh, sorry.
you know that that's
The decisive battle has been one, but it doesn't mean that the cleanup doesn't continue.
Right, so that's what's going on. That's what that is meant by that.
Eventually the cleanup will be done. Eventually the cleanup will be completed.
Yeah. You know what else is on the run?
Band. Band is on the bands.
Yeah.
And so there is still this need.
for us as Christians to distinguish between the clean and the unclean.
Right? And so for us now, right, who are Gentile Christians who are never called to keep those
commandments of the first place, right? What we're called to do is to understand this as being
as clean and unclean as being concerned with action.
rather than things.
Yeah.
Right.
And that was the goal of discriminating between the animals and discriminating with these
other things, right.
The goal of that was to be able to discriminate between clean and unclean actions, attitudes,
thoughts, desires, right.
That was the goal.
Right.
Again, this is not a making spiritual, this is a continuation of...
the heart, right? The spirit, meaning the Holy Spirit of the Torah, right? The Spirit of God,
speaking in the Torah. For all people who make that distinction, right? And
you know, as Father Andrew mentioned, people still sing now and then.
Yeah, right? Even people who have been baptized, who have been washed, right? Who have been purified.
We're very glad.
they still will sin. Right? And so now we have the process of repentance,
absolution forgiveness, right, that allows us to maintain now not a physical sanctuary,
right? But ourselves as the sanctuary in which the Holy Spirit dwells. Yep. Yep.
All right. Well, that was a good, I was going to use the word beefy, but I don't want to tempt anybody.
second week. That's not
only week for some of some
people to sing. Shrimp.
It was not a shrimpie first half.
It was a good solid mushroomy.
Mud buggy. First half and we're
going to go ahead and take our
first break and we right back
with the second half of Lord
Spears podcast. Father
Andrew Stephen Damick and
Father Stephen DeYoung will be
back in a moment to take your
Lord.
of spirits. Give them a call at 855-237-2346. That's 855-AF radio.
The cast will read the myths. We'll recount the legends. And we'll ask how they point us in one
way or another to the most high- We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the father Andrew
Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung. If you have a question call now at 855-236-
seven, two, three, four, six. That's eight five, five,
a, f radio.
Welcome back, everybody. I see the call board is lighting up.
Yeah, we're going to take some calls when they get
slotted in there, but I just want to say we currently have
as far as I'm aware, 11 countries listening right now. So hello,
our fellow Americans but also hello Brazil hello Norway
Sweden, Canada, Mexico, Spain, Canada, United Kingdom, Germany, and Malaysia.
It's pretty good.
And we haven't hit, we haven't hit all continents so far yet.
I don't think um actually you said,
you said, you know, Stan twice.
Did I Brazil?
I always did.
Oh, I did.
So yeah, well, there you go.
I mean, I give the kidnucka Stanies a hard times.
It's fine. It's fine. It's okay. Well, some guy claimed earlier that Texas was the greatest country in the world, which I
Understand how Texans feel about Texas and that's great. That's lovely. You could go visit their embassy in London, but
But it's like
I mean that whole thing where they sold their sovereignty to pay off debts
No offense Texans. I'm just saying what next you're gonna say the United States isn't a country come on, bro
No?
Like, you can't.
The day.
We got political nation states. You know who needs them?
Yeah, also
You guys are gonna play that whole like commercial intro at the beginning of every episode are you?
I don't know, you know, hey, that's like way too long man nice long break
That's like way too long and I don't know about this Richard Rohobeth character. You're doing the show but
Like if people have to sit through that they're Richard Rebombe
They're not gonna listen live. They're gonna skip it.
about. Yes. Yes. Slide that slider right over to the end of the beginning. Yeah. Yeah.
They'll sit to it once or twice. Yeah. Anyway.
All right. Yes. Okay. Well, let's go ahead and take a few calls. So we have,
we have Alex calling. So Alex, welcome to the Lord of Spirits podcast.
Thank you. I'm stoked to be here. All right. Well, we are stoked likewise to have you.
So what is on your mind, Alex?
Yeah. Well, first of all, I just want to say I super appreciate you guys
delving into the Torah.
I was Torra observant for part of my life.
And since coming into the church, I've really wondered about a lot of these
questions. And so really appreciate it.
I want to bring back what we're learning right now to a point that
Father Stephen made in the last episode about the reasoning of St. James and the council to
Russelam. Okay, next chapter of Matthew. Right, so James's argument is based upon this distinction
between the nations that are coming to worship the God of Israel and the Jewish nation, a difference
that seems to persist in his understanding.
And for that to make sense.
right like the Jewish nation would need to continue being defined to some degree by its
charter in their specific obligations according to the Torah. So things like circumcision.
And even some of the things that we're talking about tonight and with respect to the temple
specifically. So I was wondering, I know that a lot of this teaching is geared towards
and fathers even said we who are Gentile Christians, but there are a lot of Orthodox Christians
to
according to that definition of the Torah,
you know, came from the Jewish nation
or circumcised, et cetera.
And so I was wondering to what degree does this distinction
that James identified continue to persist?
If not historically, then at least like in theory,
I'm wondering if you could unpack that.
Yeah, we did talk about that a little bit last time.
The first thing that comes to mind to me
And...
You know, obviously I'm going to ask Father to mostly expand on this because this is based on what stuff he said.
One is that, you know, in the first century,
Acts chapter 15,
Jewish Christians living as Jews in community is very much a thing.
You know, so it's a live controversy at the time, right?
This is not individual people with Jewish ancestry.
This is Communities.
communities of people that have this history, this background, this community identity.
But one of the other things that I remember you said, Father, and maybe you could
expand on this a little bit is, and this was, this is especially what I've talked about the end
of the episode, was that the ways of life that we're discussing are done in community. These are
not like, oh, I have some ancestry that is this, or I used to be this, right? It's whole communities
of people and this is why then you meant
For instance, the idea of like what if for instance there were mass conversions of people in Israel in the modern state of Israel becoming Orthodox Christians, what would their version of Orthodox Christianity look like in terms of the practical observances, you know, would it potentially incorporate some things that other Orthodox Christians are not doing.
But ultimately that would kind of be in their hands to work that out as to how that would apply to them.
So that was my understanding and takeaway from from last time.
I don't know father.
I'm actually me or whatever needs to be done to.
Well, that's kind of the broad strokes, right?
Yeah, I mean, just functionally, literally in history, Judea was destroyed by the Romans.
Right.
Not just Jerusalem in 8070, but after the Barcoque were a rebellion.
monstrous bru-
brutal de-judicization project all across.
Right, Judea, and that ended Jewish Christianity
as such, right?
That's why there's not a Jewish Orthodox church,
like there's a Greek Orthodox church, right?
Or, you know, an Alexandria or the other church
in Egypt, right?
That's just functionally why it's functionally what happened.
And by the way...
There are references to this in our Holy Week books that a lot of I don't care anymore.
A lot of wild-eyed lips don't understand.
In one of our translations, it literally says, now is the nation of the Jews destroyed
and they get all upset, right?
Oh no, anti-Semitism.
And it's like, no, this is talking about a historical fact.
Yeah, a historical event.
This is something that historically happened.
Did it occur?
right? It's not calling for anything against anyone. It's not, right? This is
talking about what happened, right? And theories about what it was that was
done that brought about the judgment of the Romans destroying Judea are not a
new thing either. So for example, Josephus in one place says he thinks it
happened.
because of a herod killing St. John the Baptist.
And at another place he seems to suggest,
although some people think this is an interpolation,
but he at least seems to suggest that it's
because they killed St. James the brother of Jesus
on the temple mount.
Right, so that way of thinking is not like an anti-Semitic way of thinking,
the idea that it might be because of what happened to Jesus.
That's not an anti-s...
Semitic way of thinking. That's the way Jewish people thought about it.
Right? Jewish people thought about it. Why is God bringing this judgment upon us?
What did we do? And there were suggestions of different righteous people who were murdered.
For example, that could have brought about that kind of judgment.
And by the way, you see the same kind of thinking from later Orthodox Christians when Constantinople falls.
Oh, yeah.
The writings of monks after it happened
and our full of, it's because we did this, it's because we did that. That's why God brought this judgment on us.
So there's, there's not particularly any specific about that. And so just functionally, there was
under Saint James and his immediate successors, essentially what we would today call a Jewish Orthodox church,
Church centered in Jerusalem. That was the Mother Church for the whole church.
In fact, the concept of
of a mother church developed out of the Jerusalem church.
Yeah, and there's a lot of hymns are ero.
For, well, and sorry, Constance and Opal.
Yeah.
There's a lot of hymns that refer to Jerusalem
as the mother of the churches.
Yeah.
And that's the only church that is described
in those terms in our liturgical tradition.
Yeah.
And that church was destroyed.
The Jerusalem Patriarchate is a successor church
church. It just is, right? I mean, functionally, all of the bishops from St. James until 8070 were
Jewish. In fact, several of them were members of Jesus' family, like St. James was.
And then after that, it's Greek converts.
Right? So there is an unbroken...
apostolic succession in Jerusalem. I'm not saying that. Right. But I'm saying that the character
of the Church of Jerusalem after AD 70 and before AD 70 is very different. Right. Because
those Gentile converts, successors after AD 70 did not continue to practice circumcision,
did not continue to keep kosher, did not continue to do the ceremonial washings that Saint James did.
Right, they they didn't because they're Gentiles and that was pretty firmly established at the church by that point already that that
Even though they were now the Bishop of Jerusalem that didn't make them Jewish
And so yeah, the way that that would have to be restored like Father Andrew said it they would have to be a
Kind of mass conversion that restored that church as a thing
Right individual Jewish people joining
the Greek church, the Antiochian church, the Russian church, right? Very good. Happy when it happens, right?
But
one by one, right, they don't
constitute the kind of thing, right? So in the same way if there was such a mask conversion like I suggested could happen in Israel, right? The chief rabbit it
some vast swath of the religious Jews in
in Israel today were to
convert to Orthodox Christianity and sort of reconstitute that church. You'd have a process just like
what happened when the gospel went to Greece or went to Russia or went to where there's sort of a
sifting, a transformation, a transfiguration of the culture within Christ and Christianity,
So that you produce Greek Christianity, Russian Christianity, but in the case...
of Jewish Christianity being restored, we know that those things, those things that are actually in
the Torah, not things that were added later or things that other things, right? But the things that
are in the Torah at least, we know for sure come from God. So it's a lot easier to sift.
Right. And so I think that, and I hope it happens someday, that if we had those kind of mass
conversions from Judaism.
that the reconstituted kind of Jewish Orthodox church that would produce would probably be Torah observant.
But in a something they would have to work out for themselves, not theory, the rest of us say, oh, this is what you should be doing.
Right. Yeah. We the rest of the church would not impose that on them. It would be something they work out and they would have to sift, right.
What of this is actually from the Torah and what of this is stuff that happened later. What of this is stuff that we added that's kind of anti-Christian in the name.
nature, right? That obviously would have to go. Right? So there would be a lot of things
that it isn't just like a one for one, right? Like everything they're doing now would just
continue, right? But I think a substantial recognizable amount that is direct from the
or what? Does that make sense for you Alex?
Yes, yes and no.
Yes and no.
Honestly, because I think that the answer doesn't seem to, at least to me, on the face that
do justice to sort of mandated nature of what's in the Torah.
It doesn't really make sense to me that if you had, and it's a fair point that Father
Andrew made and that you made in the previous episode about, there was a difference between
people coming in on math, there's like a group.
as a nation of sorts versus individuals.
But I don't know that the argument is true that
like a, that an individual isn't mandated
given certain things, right?
In other words, they're only mandated to do X, Y, Z
or keep coast or whatever.
If they happen to be in a community that's already doing that,
but also be, I don't follow the notion
that it's correct.
wouldn't provide that instruction.
If this line of thought is coming from,
sorry, if the transformation will be coming from the fact that it's mandated in the Torah versus like,
okay, well, this is sort of the character of your nation, right?
So that's where I'm at, but I understand it's not an easy issue and I appreciate the input and the answers.
Let's
We just throw two quick things that might help with a couple of those things.
One is that the Torah is what constitutes them as a nation.
That is their identity as a nation, right?
Because it's not, I mean, we have these separate categories.
But the Torah is not only religious commandments.
It's also their constitution and declaration of independence and, right, like that's, that
is what makes them a nation, right?
And then the other...
thing is we have to talk about what makes an individual Jewish. Yeah. Right. And
and we now have these modern ethnic categories about what makes a person
Jewish. Right. So we would understand that a person who's never been in a
synagogue in his life. Right. Has never had any connection to it. Isn't
circumcise, right? But he goes and he does 23 and me turns out
he's like 85% Jewish, well that person is Jewish, right? But that person in the
ancient world would not have been considered Jewish.
What they, what would make that person Jewish would be being part of a Jewish
community. Right? So identity is not an individual thing, it's a collective
thing in the ancient world that the Torah is speaking into.
Yeah, right.
Yep.
So
I don't think the commandments are directed to individuals based on their ethnicity or DNA.
I think they're directed to individuals,
qua members of a community. So I hope that helps a little bit, maybe in terms of where we're
coming from at least. You may still not buy it, but I hope it helps you understand the point we're
making. I agree with you guys, but let me take so much time. Thank you. All right, thanks for calling
Alex. We're going to take a couple more calls before we move forward and we've got Anthony calling.
So in.
Anthony apparently has a question about ritual sacrifice.
Anthony, welcome to Lord of Spirits podcast.
I thank you.
Good evening.
So are you from the Northeast of the United States?
I am.
Yes.
So is it correctly pronounced Antony?
Antony.
Yeah, little Antony.
Yeah.
OK.
All right.
Or Tony.
Yeah.
So you guys have spoke.
about death as being sort of incidental in the whole process of the sacrifice and how
the most important aspects of sacrifice and worship is the fellowship meal with God.
And I guess I was thinking about the ritualized aspect of it.
That's the death of the animal is not really ritualized.
But...
the eating doesn't seem ritualized either.
Like compared to, say, like a modern Passover Seder,
for example, where it has steps in the meal itself
or even a Eucharistic service that has many,
has a very ordered aspect of the whole meal
if you wanna look at the services of the entire meal, right?
It seems to be that the ritual is more about the separation.
of the animal, the separation of the kind of animal and the portioning of how the animal
is butchered and things like that.
So I guess my question is can you clarify your argument of what is ritualized or not ritualized
is or is not important to sacrifice and the worship.
It might be related to what we've been talking about tonight in terms of cleaning and cleaning
separation.
Does that make sense? I hope it makes sense.
Yeah. Well, I mean, one thing I'll just say on its face,
and you can check this for yourself if you do a,
just do a word search on the word eat in Leviticus,
which it appears a whole bunch of times, actually.
78 times in the ESV, because I just checked.
And it constantly references who may eat what,
where exactly it must be eaten,
and on what times and days and
so forth. So like there's already all of these kinds of sanctifications that
is to say settings apart going on. Right. So I don't I I I that's clearly
ritualization. Right. At the very least. And off the top of my head, I don't
remember other details, but certainly like which parts can be eaten who who is
allowed to eat which parts. All of that is in there as well.
I don't know, fathers, are there other details here that are not coming to mind or in my?
Well, yeah, the where and the when that you mention in terms of where the priest eat and when
and those kind of things that things have been to be eaten at certain times and before certain times.
But also with and the portioning, the butchering which as you mentioned is highly detailed,
right? That's all about who gets to eat what?
That?
Right, which part gets...
burned and offered to God that way and then which parts get eaten by the priests and which parts get eaten by the people bringing the sacrifice right and then which parts are not to be eaten and are to be disposed of right that that's all related to eating.
But the other big thing to note about killing is a lot of the sacrifices including a lot of the sin offerings were wheat cakes.
Yeah, which I mean technically I guess you're killing the Wii when you plug it, but I mean
there's drink offerings too. You're stretching to call that killing, right? But even
when you're offering sin offerings, right, with weak cakes, again, the concern is who each eats
which cake, which ones are burned, right, how they're burned, when and where they're burned, to
get to offer them to God, and then what's eaten by who in terms of the rest of them. So part of
the eating thing is that the offerings are not don't always
have to be killed, but they are always food.
Yeah.
Does that help? Do we have to pronounce an antnee?
In pronounce the hell everyone.
Oh, well that's great.
Yeah, I did that help.
And I don't know if that, um, yeah, it's interesting, I guess, how even a Passover
that the rituals within the eating itself is not
of the where and what and who, but it's like the parts of it.
Right?
Like the elements in the meal.
Yeah.
And I mean, that developed later.
And you better remember, and a lot of it is developed in reaction to and based on the Christian
Eucharist.
Yeah.
Not vice versa.
Um, and I think it's also worth noting that if you were to attempt to reconstruct the
ritual life of ancient Israel.
only by reading exactly what's in Leviticus,
I don't think you could succeed in doing it.
Right, it's in many cases, it's a kind of outline.
So there may well be things going on
that are just simply not written there, you know.
Like it's interesting, like even in some early Christian texts,
sometimes they'll say things like,
and this will be in the liturgical text,
it'll say something like,
and the bishop says the usual prayers.
You know, so which that doesn't help you if you're trying to reconstruct something out of nothing.
So yeah, I don't think we should assume that everything that they were doing is exactly what's written in Leviticus.
Because if you just simply do exactly what's there into nothing else, a lot of that would be pretty brief kind of cursory stuff.
You know, but it strikes me in a lot of it as being a kind of an outline.
So, alright.
Thank you.
Thank you Anthony. All right, well, we're going to take one more call. We have Kade calling. So Kade, welcome to Lord of Spirits podcast.
Hello. Thanks for having me. Yeah, sure.
Yeah, so I guess I'll just give right to my question then.
I was wondering in relation to death by holiness and the idea that's been discussed on the podcast of the total freedom of God.
So...
I guess the the crux of the question is it seems like God can pick and choose when to apply death by holiness.
Um, like.
So I guess I'm just not sure how that process plays out.
Because even in this episode so far you've mentioned like that put the reason for the atonement and things is because of the potential of death by holiness.
So I guess I'm trying to understand where the
potential crosses over if that's just something that is like we aren't God so we don't know or if
there's more kind of going on. All right it's a good question. What do you think Father?
Does God turn the death by holiness on and off at some times or what's going on?
Well so the way it's presented to us in Scripture which of course is all you know
that's all we can know about God is what God has revealed about Himself to us right?
is that
That the other option, the other thing that can happen for death by holiness to not happen
is that God can withdraw.
Now, even that's a metaphor, because obviously God isn't in one place that he leaves that
place.
That's not what we're saying.
It's a metaphor, sort of, analogical language.
But it's the difference between the flood and the tower of Bable.
the difference between
the destruction of the northern kingdom of Israel and the exile of the southern kingdom.
Right, so the threat is either Israel gets consumed in its sin or God departs from them.
And there are examples of this scripture, obviously the big one being the exile, right?
Ezekiel sees God leaving the temple.
Right because of the...
of the people. But we also see it on a personal basis, for example, the Holy Spirit departing from
Saul at a certain point in his life, the first king, not Saul of Tarsus, the first king of Israel.
So this is the other sort of possibility, right? Now, if the question is, why does God sometimes
used to depart and sometimes stays and people die.
That's something we can't know, right?
But we know that both of us are going to get into here in the second half and the third
half.
Why exactly God departing is just as much of a threat, right?
as you know, him staying and people dying.
But, and this is right in, in some...
51 or Psalm 50, this is what David is praying, right?
Take not your Holy Spirit from me.
All right, he sees after what he's done.
Oh, no, right?
The God could withdraw his Spirit from me
because of my wickedness and my sinfulness
and this blood on my hands.
All right, and he prays that that won't happen, right?
He knows he needs to be purified and cleansed
and forgiven so that the Spirit of God
can remain, can remain with him.
Right. So I got yes, has an option there, right? He decides to do one or the other as it's presented to us in scriptures. Right. But why he decides one or the other when and where.
The details of how that all works, even what exactly it means to withdraw.
Are things were humans, right? That we can't fully understand. That's the language we've been given to talk about it.
Okay, yeah, that helps a lot because I was thinking of it as he either, you're either
dying by holiness or God does nothing but that makes much more sense when it's kind of
the withdrawal or the death by holiness.
Yeah, I mean, whatever it is that God does, and I think it's really important to really
take this seriously, whatever it is that God does is the best thing for everyone, whatever
it is he does because
God is love. Right? Yeah.
So like anionis and safira, we don't like to imagine that that was the best thing for
them, but that was, if we believe that God truly loves, that was the best thing that could
happen for them. Now God knows way more about what would have happened had that not happened
to them, what, you know, what their lives would have been like after that. We do not know we
it only speculate.
But God is doing exactly the best thing for everyone involved always, always.
So anyway.
All right.
Thank you very much, Cade.
We're going to go ahead and move on.
Get off of Ma's.
Sorry.
Wrong.
I don't even know what to do with this guy.
Apparently, he's.
Yes.
No, but I see.
who have seen them all.
So yeah, so now, second half, I think this is the latest
we've ever started a second half.
Could be.
Yeah, I'm not.
We're in for it guys.
Buckle up.
A lot of sleep tonight.
That's it.
Yeah, this one we're talking about worship.
We're talking about the Brats of potato chips.
Yeah, we're gonna start talking about.
Unmute your mic when you put in the potato chips though,
please, if you don't mind.
I'm not eating potato chips.
I was saying that I hope our list
Brought snack for this long journey on which they haven't barked. Okay. Okay. Okay. If they're baked right then then they're kind of legit
Yeah, well we just had someone in the chat say like you know, continuing because I guess this is this is a thought
Experiment that people love it's interesting. You know, what if there were a Jewish community of Orthodox Christians
Someone asked the question like wait. How could they actually completely follow the whole Torah because there's no temple
How are they offering animal sacrifices?
So buckle up, welcome to the second half.
You're tracking.
Yeah, here we go.
Yeah, yeah.
Right.
So when we're talking about worship in scripture and we're so
we're focusing here on the Torah, right?
Worship of the Torah, we have to talk about worship space.
We have to talk about dedicated places of worship.
Because that's the only kind of worship there is in the Torah.
So I have to say sorry to
some of, not all, but some of our Protestant friends who
want to insist that the church is not a building or the church didn't have
buildings and center, center, center, that's just not accurate.
There were dedicated spaces of worship at the same whether we're talking
about the patriarchs in Genesis building altars in particular places.
Yeah, they did just pull out their their kitchen table.
Right.
Or the coffee table.
And they just build a different one every time they made a sacrifice, right?
they build and out.
to place because they had an encounter with God there and that became a holy place, a
sacred place, a place of worship.
Right?
Yeah.
And then of course this becomes super obvious when we get to the Torah itself being given
because huge focus of a massive part of Exodus is the building of the Tabernacle.
Then the Leviticus, the dedication of the Tabernacle.
as we've just talked about, maintaining the purity of the tabernacle.
And then of course the temple, which is a dedicated place where God is worshiped.
And that's all that happens there.
And it's built in a particular way, structured and designed in a particular way,
based as we've talked about before on the heavenly sanctuary into which Moses entered on the top of Mount Sinai.
See Hebrews.
So, worship is at a particular place constructed dedicated.
set up for that purpose in the Torah. That's how worship works. Now that said, that said,
there is also obviously still space within the Torah, right? For what we might call a home
alter, right? And later times would be around the hearth, but prayer, right? And
you know, the singing and recitation of Psalms, these kind of things, taking place in the home
on the road during life, right? So it's not that like,
right? None of that was allowed outside the temple to the tabernacle, right? Like you're
not allowed to sing like Psalm 23 while you're working your field, right? Or you're not allowed
to pray with your family, right?
But particular elements of worship, particularly offerings, sacrificial offerings, were restricted
to a particular place, a particular time.
And this is a product, as we've talked about before, and we won't go into all this again,
but a product of the split between the father, the head of the household, and the priesthood
that happens with Moses.
an Aaron and then with the Golden Calf with the Levites, right? But even though, again,
these particular types of worship are restricted to being administered by this particular priesthood
in a particular place, a particular time. There are still elements of priesthood that still
fall within the Father's head of the family, leading in prayer, these other kind of activities,
Right. Yeah.
So the first commandment about worship in the Torah has to do with morning and evening worship in the Tabernacle, in the Book of Exodus.
Yep.
Chapter 30 to be specific.
Okay.
Sorry, your volume was kind of jumping up and down there for a second.
I was like, is something going wrong with him?
Is it, are we back to season one, so to speak?
Anyway, yes, yes, I need the Mexican radio back.
Yes, Xs, chapter 30 versus one through eight.
You shall make an altar on which to burn incense.
You shall make it of a quiche of wood.
A qubit shall be its link and a qubit its breath.
shall be square and two-
Cubits shall be its height and just as a comment everybody.
Cubits is the space between your elbow and like the end of your fingers.
So it's about a foot and a half roughly.
Two Cubits shall be its height.
Its horns shall be of one piece with it.
You shall overlay it with pure gold.
It's topping around its sides and its horns.
And you shall make a molding of gold around it.
And you shall make two golden rings for it.
Under its molding on two opposite sides of it, you shall make them.
And they should be holders for poles with which to carry it.
shall make the poles of a key.
and overlay them with gold, and you shall put it in front of the veil that is above the ark of the testimony.
In front of the mercy seat, well, we know what that means, the lid, the lid that is above the testimony,
where I will meet with you. And Aaron shall burn fragrant incense on it every morning when he dresses the lamps,
he shall burn it, and when Aaron sets up the lamps at twilight, he shall burn it, a regular incense offering before the Lord throughout your generations.
So this is
Our first and most basic pattern of worship,
the offering of incense with prayers
at the trimming of the lamps in the morning,
meaning sunrise, and the lighting of the lamps
in the evening at sunset.
This becomes the pattern for,
as in the Orthodox Church,
the Matins and Vesper services,
the Orthodox and Vesper services,
where incense is offered with prayers
at the lighting of the lamps, at sunset, and the trimming of the lamps at sunrise.
Okay, so sometimes when I bring this up, right, because of course, we should worship God in the way
He has told us to worship Him, right? Not in some other way that we invent. People will say,
Well, that's the Old Testament. It's like, yes, that is the Torah.
exactly where that comes from. But here's the thing, when we get to the New Testament, if you ask me,
where does it say we should stop offering animals as sin offerings? Right? Or where does it say we should stop
celebrating the day of atonement? Or where does it say that Gentile Christians don't need to keep
kosher or any of these other things where there's some kind of disjunction in the way in which
the Torah's commandments are fulfilled in the New Covenant. I can point you to those things to the New Testament.
Right? Can you point me to where in the New Testament it says, stop offering incense at morning and evening?
Where God says, oh yeah, I don't want you to do that for me anymore. For reasons.
reasons.
Yet, it's not a thing to do with Christ.
I guess they have to have something to do with Christ.
Those reasons why we don't offer incense anymore,
but I'm in a loss.
Yeah, I mean, there's a bunch of details about worship
that are clearly transformed, altered, whatever,
but this isn't one of them.
Yeah, when that happens, we're told.
Yeah, and we know apostles tell us, right?
And we know that historically,
incense continued to be offered morning and night.
It just is a thing.
There's never a point in the history of
orthodox worship where you don't have that. Right. It never stopped and that's related to the fact that we're never told it should. Right. Yeah. So the only reason to think that this commandment would still apply in terms of how God wants to be worshiped
would be if you start with the presupposition that Christianity is this new religion that
starts
of the New Testament and so everything in the Old Testament is irrelevant.
Yeah, that has to be sort of constructed from the ground up.
Right. And so only things in the New Testament are relevant.
Right. And while there may be certain segments of the self-identified Christian world who
like to do that, well Jesus didn't say anything about blank.
Right? Yeah.
If you all, if you say the only things that are sins are things that Jesus specifically
mentioned as being sins, right?
You're going to end up with a weird moral code.
Yeah.
Well, if you leave out the rest of the Bible.
Right.
There's, right?
Yes.
There's a lot of things he didn't mention that are really bad.
Right?
He didn't feel the need to specifically mention.
the reason is, as we said last time.
Christ is all the time talking about applying the Torah. He assumes you're
familiar with it. St. James in his letter telling the Gentiles they only had to
keep those four commandments says in the same letter, Moses has been preached in
every place in the synagogues. He's assuming everyone's familiar with the Torah.
Right? He sees that as relevant. If St. James was constructing a new religion
why would he say that? Why would that be relevant? So clearly that is a false premise
and just a plain reading of the scriptures tells us that the most basic structure of our worship
of God should be the offering of incense at morning and evening with prayers.
And of course,
In explaining how prayer works, prayer is compared to incense in the Old Testament.
Yeah, and Psalm 141, 141, depending on which version.
First, too, which you come to Vespers.
This is one of the Psalms you'll hear, but you know, that my prayer rise and I cite as incense.
Right.
And so since the offering of incense could only take place at the Tabernacle or the temple,
Right, in your covenant.
The pattern, nonetheless began of morning and evening prayer in the home.
Right.
So morning and evening prayer in the home is derivative of the morning and evening offering
of incense, not vice versa.
So Mattens and Vespers, orthos and Vespers do not come from, hey, we're all going to say
our morning and evening prayers anyway.
Let's just all get together and do it together.
It's the opposite.
The offering of incense with prayers takes place and those who aren't able to participate in it
pray at home as a means of participating in it when they're not able to gather together.
Right. So that's the most sort of basic structure of worship.
The next structure up, of course, is then going to be
the sacrifice is more broadly.
The offering of incense is a type of sac-
sacrifice. The same language is used of it in terms of being a pleasing aroma in God's nostrils
that's used of the burning of offerings to him in sacrifices. And in the same way that the blood
that is the product of the sacrificial animal is used for cleansing and purification, the smoke
that comes from the burning incense is used for cleansing and purification.
So the daily sacrifice.
The original cycle took place,
sacrifices every day, whole structure of sacrifice,
including sin offerings,
grain offerings, drink offerings.
It was happening every day in the temple
until its destruction.
And as the book of Acts shows us
that we've talked about on the show
before to some controversy,
Christians continued to participate in that
up until the temple was destroyed.
And at that time,
Right
At that time, until the temple was destroyed functionally for Christians, the Eucharist was
functioning as an additional sacrificial offering by the Christian community when it met on the Lord's
day. They would go to the synagogue on the Sabbath and then they would gather together to celebrate
the Eucharist just as Christians on the Lord's Day. And so the Eucharist
was offered there was a new sacrificial offering with a new priesthood. A new priesthood appointed
to an insert that particular sacrifice, not the others. Then he'd go to the temple and do the others.
And as Hebrews points out, those doing the sacrifices in the temple who weren't Christians couldn't
come and eat from the altar of the Eucharist. Because this is a new priesthood with a new sacrifice
received from Jesus.
the Messiah. And that sacrificial offering of the Eucharist, see our Eucharist episode
for this in much more detail, but very short version is a means by which those eating it
participate in Christ's sacrifice in his self offering, which happened at one point in history.
But we come to participate in it ritually within the Eucharist.
So Christ's sacrifice, self-offering of Jesus the Messiah, fills the sacrificial system
full, fulfills it because it does what those daily sacrifices did, but does it once and
for all.
And so when the temple is destroyed and those daily sacrifices cease, pretty much immediately
the Eucharist starts to be offered daily.
Right. Christians don't misbeat on that. Right. And in fact, you will find the early Christians writing, well, yeah, the temple's gone, but we didn't need it anymore anyway.
Right. Because Christ has done what those offerings did.
Yeah. So this idea that some people have like, oh, you know, that temple has to be rebuilt in order for, I don't know, whatever to happen. It depends on what kind of dispensationalist you are, I guess.
Yes.
not a thing in early Christianity. Like, there's never a sense of we need to retake Jerusalem
so that we can rebuild that temple and start putting bulls and goats and sheep up on that
altar again.
Right. And it wouldn't be a thing to answer the question from comments. It wouldn't be
a thing for a Jewish Orthodox church either. Right. Right. Yep. Right. Because they would
embrace Jesus as their Messiah, right, and would be per-
participating in the self offering of the Messiah in the Eucharist, right?
So they would not bring those back.
And that's not a big deal, by the way, to most Jewish people.
The people dragging the genetically engineered red cows around Jerusalem right now
are a weird fringe group that is not mainstream Judaism.
Most religious pious Jews think that's ridiculous.
Okay. Um, yeah. So, but I love a good red half our cult. Yeah. But one more bit we've
before we leave this. And I know we've talked about this other show before, but every episode is someone's first.
Right. Yes. And so there may be somebody out there who, uh, especially if they're not orthodox or Roman Catholic,
meaning if they're one of our Protestant friends or someone else.
Might have
got caught up on the whole idea that the Eucharist is a sacrificial offering.
Right. Because some of the Protestant reformers explicitly say it isn't. Some say explicitly it is,
but some say it isn't. Right. So there are segments of of Protestantism that would take great
issue with that, others that would just find it foreign and a weird concept. But
St. Paul, at 1 Corinthians 10 verses 14 through 22, there is no way around the
this in the text. There's no way around this in the Greek text. He says the Eucharist
is a sacrifice. Yeah, and you have to understand what a sacrifice is. It's a shared meal with
your God. That's key to understanding why this is the case. Okay, so first Corinthians 10,
verses 14 through 22. We've probably read this 10 times on the show, but it is worth hearing
again. Therefore my beloved flee from my Dollar Tree. I speak as to sense.
people judge for yourselves what I say. The cup of blessing that we bless, is it not a participation
in the blood of Christ? The bread that we break, is it not a participation in the body of Christ?
Because there is one bread we who are many are one body for we all partake of the one bread.
Consider the people of Israel are not those who eat the sacrifices, participants in the altar.
What do I imply then that food offered to idols is anything or that an idol is anything? No, I
I imply that would pay in sacrifice.
They offer to demons and not to God. I do not want you to be participants with demons.
You cannot drink the cup of the Lord and the cup of demons. You cannot partake of the table
the Lord and the table of demons. So we provoke the Lord to jealousy. Are we stronger than he?
I love those good rhetorical questions.
So
You may have heard all through there.
Participation, participants, partake.
participate, right? That's all the same word in Greek. Yeah. And then even at the end, you get that parallel cup of the Lord cup of demons. Yeah, table the Lord table of demons.
Keedania all the way through. Right? Yeah. So verse 18, he talks about those who eat the sacrifices on the altar at the temple in Jerusalem. Okay.
Then he talks about the sacrifices that are offered on pagan altars to idols and thereby to demons.
And then he talks
about the Eucharist. And he explicitly says all three of those are functioning the same way.
Yeah, the difference is who you're in communion with.
Right. Who you're in communion with. Right? So, there's just no way around it. He says
it's a sacrifice. He says it does what sacrifices do. It works the way sacrifices work.
Yeah, so this is one of the big transformations that happens in applying the Torah, right?
The Sacr-
prices of the Torah, get summed up in, subsumed into and expanded, frankly, in the Eucharist.
Right. Filled up to overflowing, filled full, full filled, right? Not done away with. Right?
They're encapsulated. I mean, just think about it. You've got a grain offering. You've got a drink
offering. You've got a thank offering. It's a sin offering, right?
It's not that those are all done away within replaced.
Right?
It's that those are all summed up in the one offering, ultimately the one offering of Christ.
In which the Eucharist is a participation.
Okay.
So then finally, in addition to those sort of daily sacrifices, then the daily worship,
right, with the offering of incense and that kind of thing, there's the cycle of feasts.
Yeah, this is another one that we get a lot of questions about.
People are like, well, why don't we do this feast?
What do we do this?
fees. And actually, certain five percent of those questions are we do that feast. Yeah.
You made out of understood a feast that we do properly to see the connection. And sometimes
our translations don't help. But right. So there are some where there's an obvious and very
direct correspondence. Right. So PASCA Passover. Yeah. Right. Is the Greek word for Passover? Yeah.
It's Easter is the
in Passover. So I don't want to be mean here, but I know of Protestants who love, you know,
elements of Jewish tradition they've encountered and they will celebrate Passover and then they
will celebrate Easter. It's like, it's, you're doing Passover and then you're doing Passover.
Yeah. You're doing the Jewish Passover, the Christian Passover, either you're not even Jewish.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
sort of trans Jewish, I think. Is that rude? Referring to like Hebrew roots, people
as trans Jewish? I don't know. And then like actual Jewish people are cis Jewish.
Head hooks. I can't all the world tonight. If I canceled now,
fully canceled people scratching their heads in 10 countries.
That's all right.
If I put my figure on something should I take it off?
Okay, so.
Yes, Pentecost.
Yes, Pentecost is a feast of weeks.
Say more direct chorus fondance with Pentecost.
Are we talked about that some more a couple episodes ago?
Oh, yes, yes, in the land episode.
The addiction, right, ecclesiastical New Year September 1st in the Orthodox Church.
Right around Rosasana, the feast of trumpets, the New Year.
Yep.
Right.
There's a direct carryover.
you read the hymn.
pornography and everything in the related iconography. There's direct
carryover
Little more subrosa little less obvious the transfiguration in the feast of booths
Which if you read the text in the Gospels it's happening during that feast
Right, and of course St. Peter famously says let's make three booths
Did I just ruin the word booths for every one by pronouncing? No, I mean you know
Some people like voiced fricatives.
Some people prefer unvoiced fricatives, you know, whatever.
I think you need to watch your language on Christian radio, my friend.
Anyway.
So, uh, and then maybe even more indirect, right, is the connection between Theophony and Hanukkah,
the Feast of Lights element.
Yeah.
It's not the most significant element of Theophony.
No, right.
Right, right. If you read read the fiatphony texts the actual
hymns closely and think about feast of lights and you'll start to see it and actually indeed like if you look in the menehan it refers to the ofteny sometimes in like the rubrics as the feast of lights.
It calls it that.
And there's there's you know dedication of temple stuff going on in there and all that all that sort of thing as well.
Yeah yeah yeah.
So.
So yeah, so...
But then there are other things, right?
So there are other things in the Hebrew Bible of the Old Testament.
There are obviously other feasts in the church, historically, that don't quite match up
with each other so neatly, right?
And so part of what we have to understand is the principle that's set out in the Torah
and then that's followed through the rest of the Hebrew Scriptures and then...
continues to be followed in the church.
And that is that when there is a new act of God,
particularly a redemptive or selfish act of God
that takes place, there is a new feast
that comes into being to commemorate it.
So one example, Purim, in Esther, right,
in Esther. Right. The people of Israel.
Well, the people of Judah who are still in Persia are, right, and those returning to Judea
are delivered, are saved through Esther and there is this new holiday, Purim, Hanukkah,
that we already mentioned.
Right.
So these are not, these are not feasts of the Torah.
These are things that come later.
Right.
And so in the same way that we saw that these sort of new acts of God, like Christ's death
in resurrection sort of
subsumes and fulfills what happened at the first Passover, the delivery from slavery in Egypt,
right? The passing from death to life. We've talked about that on the show before, right?
There are also these new acts of God which get their new feasts. So events in the life of the Theotokos
like the Annunciation that we just celebrated and that our old calendar friends will be celebrating in
in a couple of weeks. And events related to life of St. John the
honor. Right. So these new acts of God develop these new feasts and that is continued later into
church history, like the feast of the protection of the Theotokos and the feast of the exaltation of
the cross. Right. Because of course, God has continued to act in history. He didn't just stop. Right.
When the last Apostle died. Right. New stuff has come to light, dude. Right. And so,
Oh, right.
just as we see this principle of the acts of God
starting with the Passover being commemorated,
meaning remembered together, meaning made present again
together, ritually, right?
That begins with Passover, the other feasts of the Torah,
right?
That is it taken to then just be, okay, well now God is done
acting.
And so those are the feasts.
And that's it.
That's the Hebrew Scriptures.
continue as the history of God's people continues, that same principle is applied to add new
feasts. The same thing continues in the church.
Yes, indeed. And where we come back, people get killed. Death, destruction. On the third
half of the Lord of Spirits podcast, we will be right back.
Andrew Stephen Damick and fun.
or Stephen DeYoung will be back in a moment
to take your calls on the next part
of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
Forge enduring connections with Orthodox brothers.
Strengthen your faith.
encouraged and
Challenge yourself at the first ever ancient faith men's retreat.
The retreat features four engaging speakers, daily services and Sunday divine liturgy, fellowship
with like-minded Orthodox men, and more of the beautiful Antiochian Village Conference
Center in Bolivar, Pennsylvania.
Thursday, August 22nd through Sunday, August 25th.
Speakers include Hyrumunk Basil of Holy Cross monastery in Wayne, West Virginia, Father
John Strickland, author of the Paradise in Utopia Book Series, Father John Oliver,
The hosts of the AFR podcast, Hearts and Minds, and Father Michael Mark Antony,
priest at St. John Chrysostom Orthodox Church in National Tennessee.
For more information and to register, please visit store.enginefaith.com slash events.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now.
855-237-2346. That's 855-AF radio.
Welcome back everybody. Before we get all that death and so forth, we do have a caller
who has been very patiently waiting since the beginning of the second half. And this
is one of our Canadian friends, so...
Waiting in the waiting room because they...
Yeah indeed. So David, welcome to the Lord of Spirits podcast.
Hello, fathers.
How are you?
Good, how are you?
Good, a long time listener and first time caller in it's an honor.
So I'll get to my question.
I'm just wondering, is there an origin story for orthodox fast?
Like, for example, like who started it?
And did they believe that we were under the law law?
And the reason I asked that is kind of a two-part question.
the reason I'm asking it because in my church,
We're actually not allowed to out fish during the year even.
So, yeah.
So, tell me about your church that you're not allowed to out fish.
Speaking as someone who now lives in Louisiana, this is Grave Apostasy.
So, I know Father Andrew, you'd be familiar with us where Russian old believers.
and because I think you did an interview.
with Father Pim and Simon from Pennsylvania, from that
for the old.
Yeah, he's a pretty good guy too.
And so, yeah, I guess we're kind of, I don't know,
that's kind of like we don't do any services in English.
So we're kind of a little bit more old school.
We call them the pre-spless.
So.
Bezpopov, see, I'm sure Miss Pranantse.
Yeah, yes, yes, yes, exactly.
Oh, it was pretty close.
.
Yeah, yeah. So it's it's it's old church Slavonic is what we're under it like so that's that's our how our services are done in church and everything so.
But yeah, I'm just curious like it like I couldn't find anything on like who started our our fast and like say our great lend right now for example like for.
And did they believe or sort of group of people?
And did they believe that we were under the law?
Because...
You know, that's kind of my basic question, if they, yeah, there. So, yeah, you know, I mean,
this is a fascinating, this is a fascinating question, which I do not know the answer to. So,
I'm just going to speculate a little bit. Okay. So this is just pure speculation on my part.
This should be. So, yeah, it's true, right? That shellfish are forbidden under kosher.
And we've talked a little bit about kosher and clean and unclean in that kind of thing.
But it's also true that
And this is news to me, like I didn't know this detail about old believers.
As far as I know, at least no mainstream Orthodox tradition for Bid selfish,
even during fasts, like it's not something that you need to fast from,
generally speaking, right?
Okay, well, it doesn't date back to Russia like, uh, to the 1600s,
1500s. Oh, sure.
Are we packed?
Sure.
Depends our way for a long time, though.
Yeah, yeah, I know.
I mean I do know...
the general story about the old believers,
where that comes from and so forth.
But yeah, it's interesting to me
that this would be forbidden
in the old believer tradition or traditions,
I mean, cause there's a lot of groups, right?
And I wonder about that.
Like, well, number one,
for your average Rush North Rocks Christian in the 17th century,
how often is selfish actually gonna be available to him anyway?
Right? I don't know. Maybe maybe some coastal living ones it would be. I have no idea.
But I imagine for most of them, probably not, it wouldn't even be around. Although, I mean,
maybe there's some kind of crayfish in the streams of Russia that I've never heard of.
I don't know. It's entirely possible because again, I don't know anything about these things.
But yeah, I don't know. Do you have any ideas about this? You just know that this is your
practice right?
I'm asking you to meet him.
Yeah, yeah, I want to know.
I'm sorry.
I know you called it with your question,
but I have questions for you.
No, sorry.
I have no idea.
That's just a question I've always had.
It's more like if I can generalize,
even if we can just move away from our from my church,
even like, and we just say,
like, who created the whole fast,
the whole fast the way it's done.
like the answer. Yeah, yeah, go ahead father. Yeah, that I do know
nothing about, but I know you two father is the shellfish thing, the only difference you know about
before I go further. Um, like, and is it generally for bit? Yeah, I just want to ask,
is it generally forbidden like you never have selfish or is it only forbidden during fasts?
No, I'd like to throw up here, you can't have shoulders.
I think it's ever, yeah.
Okay.
Yeah.
Right.
Like we need poor, Craig.
So I don't know.
Yeah.
That's what that's what's getting
out.
Is this a one off or is it?
Yeah.
So that's not the whole tour.
We did.
We did an episode in terms of the
origins of Lent as such.
We did an episode a couple episodes
back called the season of virtue
that sort of talks about that.
the Wednesday.
and Friday fasts go back into pre-Christian Judaism in a form.
So that as far as we could tell,
I mean this, what I say as far as we could tell,
is apostolic, like they're atheists
who would agree with me that fasting
on Wednesday and Friday is apostolic.
Yeah, I mean, it's in the Dita-He or Dita-Dita.
Yeah, it's in the,
what everybody else calls the Dita-K.
So,
trans-Greek over here now.
but so.
You're not passing, Father Andrew.
Anyway, so yeah, and what it explicitly says in the D.D.
okay is it mentions that it was moved by the Christians to Wednesday and Friday.
So they would not be fasting with the hypocrites, meaning the Pharisees.
Right.
Okay.
So the Pharisees had had two days a week when they fasted.
I think it was Monday and Thursday.
Um, um,
And so that gets moved to Wednesday and Friday by Christians, right?
So that's the fasting part, right?
But if this is throughout the year that it's not just a fasting discipline, but in general in terms of what we fast from
It is the things that at the time
We're considered to be sort of the delicacies like the stuff that made food good and rich
Right and yeah as controversial as this is
uh, since uh, my metropolitan has said something similar recently, I feel like I can get away
with this one, unlike everything else I've said tonight. Um, might need some reconsideration
in our modern world, right? Because like a fast where you can eat lobster, uh, but not
like a cheap chicken sandwich seems like an odd thing to me if you're trying to avoid
delicacies right?
So at that time, right, shellfish was considered kind of garbage, right?
Like you would go out fishing and you catch all this other garbage in your net, right?
So it's sort of like, well, you can eat the good fish.
You can eat that other stuff, right?
And then, you know, enterprising Greeks learned how to cook calamari and stuff to make it
appetizing. Right. God for them.
Right. But so my thought might be, and thinking about Russia, thinking about things like
caviar, right, that maybe a lot of that seafood was considered kind of a delicacy and kind
of decadent culturally during that formative period for the old believers. And so since
That food was considered kind of a delicacy kind of decadent kind of
borderline gluttonous that you would go and consume that kind of thing, that seems to
me the likely story, as Plato would say, in terms of how that came to be based on what
we do know.
So that's our speculation, David.
What do you think of it?
Okay.
So what do you think the church fathers, like was there any, like what was the majority consensus
then did they believe about the food?
Did they all believe that every food was clean?
That's kind of, I guess, some three-part question now.
Yeah.
Well, I mean, so like fasting rules is not clean and unclean, right?
Because if it is unclean, you would never be allowed to eat it ever, right?
Yeah.
And so like, you know, the example of pork, for instance, right?
So clearly that's now considered clean because Christians eat it outside of fasting periods.
The exact details of the fasts which is again not a clean
the exact details of the fast can have varied from place to place and time to time.
Like Western fasting traditions, even before, frankly, the Roman Catholic church sort of gutted them,
Western fasting traditions were always different from Eastern fasting traditions.
Like, as far as I know, for instance, fish was almost never actually forbidden or dairy, right?
in the West, even in the ancient, ancient West. So there's variation.
on fasting. But yeah, I think that like there's no with the exception of like, you know, don't eat blood.
There's not a sense of like, well foods in general are
still divided into clean and unclean, right? And not eating blood is a separate question
from the clean unclean thing. We've talked about that on previous episodes because it's
Mark 719. Mark 719. See, I'm gonna look at this one off real quick.
Quick!
We could do a... do you even mark 719, bro?
to the Bible gateway, Batman.
All right. Yeah. Yeah.
Since it enters not as hard for the stomach
and is expelled, therefore,
thus he declared all foods clean.
There you go.
All foods are clean.
That's in red letters.
So, you know, it's really important.
Now, I mean, you know, don't go back
to your, your Nostaliyatil and tell him,
well, you know, these two dudes on a podcast
said X, Y and Z.
Thank you so much.
I'm a glutton from Louisiana.
The shrimp basket at the long john's silver.
You can't trust me on this at all.
Yeah, I'm sorry.
Nostovnik, that would be the term
for the leader of your community.
Is that right?
Nostovnik?
No, I'm not saying that you're right.
Oh, oh, Nostia.
Okay.
All right.
Yeah.
So they have the same thing.
They believe.
Okay.
So they believe that John like Chrysostom
has said that we are from
for eating those things. So, I'm like, I'd recall.
I'd be like, well, so, you know, show me, show me the money.
That's, that's, say about that.
Well, I think you should just be obedient to your spiritual father.
But that, I would be interested in finding out if that's true
and where he said that. Yes, exactly.
Exactly. Exactly.
All right. Well, thank you, David.
It's been fascinating chat with you.
Thanks for calling.
Thank you so much, Father. I appreciate it.
Alrighty. Okay. Death destruction. May hit the death don't you? Yeah. Cut off from among the people.
Parts where we're we're talking about yeah we're talking about the death penalties of the Torah
which clearly are still enforced completely in the Orthodox Church.
I'm not joking.
Yes, it's true.
Not a joke.
So it must be mean you ask.
Stay tuned.
Let's talk about it.
Right.
So first thing.
First thing.
You know, we had to talk a little bit last time about the idea that sacrifices were only for unintentional sense.
Right?
Yeah.
Unintentional robbery.
Right.
That kind of thing.
And how that doesn't really work.
really work. So there's something we have to talk about with this that doesn't really
work either.
And that's there are some folks out there who look at the death penalties prescribed in the Torah
and think that no repentance was possible. Right, which let's think this through everybody. Look at
all the things that the death penalty is prescribed for and let's assume that that gets really
applied every single time and is every time a son.
mark to his father, no sorry son, no repentance possible, I'm going to stone you to death.
Yeah. Every single time. Yeah, Israel would not have lasted a generation. Yes, right? Like
that's clearly not going on. Now you say, well, it doesn't say anything there about repentance.
Okay. It doesn't have to. That's not how the Hebrew Bible works. Example, Jonah. Yeah,
he does
say repent, Ninevites, or this bad thing will happen. He just says, yeah.
Bad thing is happening. Yes. Three days of your toast. That's what he says.
The DeYoung standard translation. You will be destroyed in three days. Yes.
That's it. He doesn't say anything about repent. Does it tell them how to repent?
what to do to repent, right?
But they all repent and the city is spared.
by God, right? So the fact that, right, this is there. And we mentioned we were talking about this earlier.
One of the lines in great compliment here in Lent, we're reading the prayer of Manasseh.
And in the at least in our Antiochian translation, the old Antiochian translation, which I hope remains with us always.
It says, the threatening towards sinners is intolerable.
That's such a great line.
Right.
So, right.
But what is this talking about?
It's not that God goes around making empty threats.
Right. Right. Right.
Like it's talking about, right?
This is a person who has grievously sinned.
Right.
And he can look at the torrentous menace of the wicked king, right, of Israel.
And he's looking and saying look at the torrent saying I know
what I deserve, right? I know what God has appointed for someone who does the things that I did,
right? I should be killed dozens of times over, right? That's the threatening he's talking about.
And he's saying, I can't live with this. Right? I can't live with it. I can't go on with this. I
need to be forgiven. This is too much of a weight for me. But he's repenting. The whole prayer is
There's one over repentance.
a beautiful prayer by the way. Listen, if you've never read it, go look this up, the prayer of
Manasa. Amazing. He's not resigning himself to the executioner's acts. Well, this is what I deserve
according to the Torah. I got to follow through on it, right? He's seeking forgiveness.
That is at the core of everything of the Torah is that you could repent. God is telling you
that this is right, what must happen to someone who does these things to drive you to repentance?
That's the purpose of that quote unquote,
threatening, right? We also have to note that the language that's used being cut off from among the people being cut off from the synagogue literally sometimes or being cut off from the ecclesia from the assembly from the church in the Old Testament, right?
That language of being cut off is kind of ambivalent.
Right, there are places that specifically say if someone does this, they must be stoned
to death.
That's very clear, stone to death.
But the cutoff from among the people language,
obviously you can see how that would be a death penalty.
But you can also see how that might refer to like exile.
Right, they're gonna be exiled from Israel.
They're gonna be exiled from the Israelite camp.
They're gonna be cast out.
Right, they're gonna be removed.
Right, and if you think about what we were saying earlier
tonight, right?
God's two options with death by Holy.
Right? Our death happens to a sinful people or he withdraws. Right? Think about the day of atonement, ritual. Right?
Sins are put on a goat. The goat takes the sins away. Removes them. Right? And so, cut off from them. The people, death, exile. Right?
Right, this unrepentant center has to be removed from the
people has to go away, right, one way or the other. But these ideas being so closely connected
is not just an ambiguity of the Hebrew phrase of the idiom, right, cut off from among the
people. These are closely allied ideas, not just in Israel, in the ancient world. Right. So think
about Socrates, our old friend Socrates.
Socrates, John.
So, right, think about the apology.
What was he sentenced to?
He was not sentenced to death.
Right.
He was sentenced to exile from Athens.
Yeah, no.
He said I'd rather drink poison.
And he chose to drink the hemlock, right, rather than be exile.
And while he was preparing to drink the hemlock, he had friends, right,
trying to smuggle him out of town.
He's like, I don't want to be smuggled out of town.
I don't want to be exiled.
Right?
Why?
It wasn't just, oh, he thought it was the most beautiful city.
Right?
This is a different view of what life means.
We as contemporary people think of life
in terms of biological life.
and death is the cessation of biological life.
And so for example, all of our medical science is just aimed at prolonging biological life for every moment possible.
That's why in the contemporary world there are so many difficult end-of-life decisions that have to be made by families and that kind of thing.
Because there's just biological life, right? Keep them breathing by force if necessary, right?
That's not how life was viewed.
in the ancient world.
Right? And this is something you can see from nature.
This is why the Greek philosophers and other people
in other places hit upon it, because you can see it in nature.
Right? There are animals that are solitary
and there are animals that run in packs.
Right? And it was very clear to them that man was a social
was a communal animal.
Yeah. I mean, from day one, you know, a baby born must have
other people.
in order to survive period. Yes. Yes. Right. It was not good that Adam was alone. Right. Right.
Um, I'm an ad-man.
And he's a rebel. So as a communal animal, right, the community of which you are apart, we were talking
about this a little earlier with a collar is what forms your identity.
at the core
of Socrates' identity was being an Athenian, and that meant particular things about his
relationship to the divine, to the gods, to the particular gods of Athens, to his relationship
to the land, being in a round Athens, for him to be exiled, even if he just went to
and sparta right wherever he would not be the same person.
As a citizen of Sparta that he was as a citizen of Athens as part of the demos of Athens.
His life as he had let it up to that time would end just as surely by exile as it would by him drinking the hemlock.
And he might be able to forge some new identity in that other place.
But he didn't want to try and do that.
Right.
So we have to understand for the Israelites and the later Jewish people, the second time of period,
their identity is formed by being part of this community.
And when the diaspora happens, during and after the exile,
and you say, well, there are Jewish people all over, right? But what do they do every place where
Where they go.
to form Jewish communities to maintain their Jewish identity.
Because without that community,
their Jewish identity vanishes in a couple generations.
That's what happened to the northern tribes of Israel.
Their Israelite identity, once they were shuffled off
to towns in Assyria and they intermarried,
and they didn't have any kind of Israelite communities,
their Israelite identity vanished in a couple generations.
I mean, it's frankly, it's just like...
you know, immigration to the United States, right?
People who form their own local communities tend to perpetuate
the identity for a while, but those who don't, you say, Oh, well,
I think some of my ancestors came from such and such a place, you know,
yeah, yeah.
And so the genetics of those people in the northern kingdom of Israel continued.
They had genetic descendants, right?
But their Israelite identity was gone.
Yeah, right. And so their descendants were Assyrians and then Babylonians, right? They were not Israelites. DNA does a matter in this case, right?
But more than that, even more than that, that's sort of the self conception of the person who's receiving this threatening.
Right is death exile, whichever.
My life is over. I'm not me anymore.
Right? The me that exists.
identity, it would be destroyed by this, right? Is the other sense in which being cut off
from the community is being cut off from life itself in a more literal sense. So think
back to going back to Genesis 3 again, not about the curse this time, but about the expulsion
from Paradise. Remember the threatening that Adam received, right? Which was if you eat
of this tree in the day that you
eat of it dying you will die. You're dead in that day on that day. And of course we've talked about
this a bunch, right? Clearly that didn't mean physical death. You didn't eat from the tree and then
fall over. Drop over, yeah. Drop dead physically, right? Though we've talked about there's physical
death and there's spiritual death. Physical death is the separation of the body from the soul.
We're talking about this a lot so you can go to past episodes, get a lot more detail. But physical
death is the sep-
of the body and the soul.
Spiritual death is the separation of the soul from God.
And as we've talked about in our episode about the soul,
our soul is really our connection to God that brings life to our bodies.
Right.
So in the day that I made a bit, he died spiritually.
He was expelled from paradise.
He was cut off from God.
Right.
And
the, when he's cut off and he's cut off from the tree of life, as we've said, as a mercy,
so he wouldn't live forever in that state. Right? He's cut off from the tree of life. Now,
what does he do now that he's in our present world? Right? Well, he needs to find ways
of restoring the life that he's lost and maintaining the life that he has.
And those means are worship and the purification that comes through sacrificial worship.
Right.
Those then become Adam and Eve's and all of their descendants, right?
Subsequent humans, that's their tether back to God who is life.
Worship, coupled with repentance, purification, transformation, that's their tether back to life.
So then...
What does it mean to be cut off from the means of worship and the means of purification?
Right? That is true spiritual death.
This is why the first two halves were groundwork for this. Right? We talked about purification from
on cleanness. How that happens. That happened in the community. In the Israel.
and then the Jewish and then the Christian community.
Right?
We talked about worship, and it's a fact,
where does that happen in the Israelite,
in the Jewish, in the Christian community?
Yep.
Right?
And so being cut off from that community means spiritual death.
And restoration to that community is the only means
of restoring that spiritual life.
And it's spiritual death that leads to physical death.
It is spiritual death that leads to physical death.
This is what's going on in interrupts states.
In enoch and Elijah not dying physically and going into heaven of the bodies of Moses
and the Theotokos being taken up into heaven.
They're not seeing decay.
as they had reconnected with the source of life.
So then, some of you may have already heeded in how do those death penalties continue
to exist in the infunction in the church in the same way they did before in the form of
excommunication.
Yeah.
In the form of excommunication because the church is the realm in which forgiveness and
purification, restoration to communion with God.
Restoration of life take place through the Eucharist through repentance forgiveness
absolution. It's where our identity is formed and that's not just identity in
terms of my sense of self. This is quite literally when we're baptized our old
self dies a new creation a new person comes into being but that person only
exist.
as part of a community of baptized and newly recreated people.
And so being cut off from all that means being cut off from that new identity,
that new life, the ability to maintain life.
The church is the realm where sacrificial worship is taking place in the Eucharist.
So, excommunication.
as death, as real death, as a threatening.
Exists for the same reason that the threatening of the death penalty of being cut off from among the people exist in the Torah.
First and foremost, to promote repentance.
Yeah, this is explicit in the passages in the New Testament.
that mention it, where you get this language of being handed over to Satan, which sounds
kind of weird and scary. It is definitely weird and scary, more scary than weird probably.
That's it. Paul says it.
But yeah, you can't, once again, you can't get away from it. Yeah, so in 1 Corinthians
5.5.
St. Paul's, this is the passage where
seen Paul's talking about the guy in Corinth who is sleeping with what is his mother-in-law
or stepmother or it's one of the two. Yeah, it's not totally clear, but it's either his mother-in-law
or his stepmother. Right. And obviously it refuses to repent. Yeah, unrepentantly. And both of those
are bad. Like there's not a better option. Yes. Both are bad. Yeah. So this is what St. Paul says
about this man, 1 Corinthians 5-5, you are to deliver this man to Satan.
for the destruction of the flesh so that his spirit may be saved in the day of the Lord.
And then similarly in 1 Timothy 1, 20, I can't remember what the what the
offenses here but he's talking about some false teachers and stuff. Okay, yeah, yeah, yeah.
that is among whom are Hamanias and Alexander whom I have handed over to Satan.
that they may learn not to blaspheme.
So in both cases, it's handing over to someone
to Satan in order of that, the first case,
so a spirit may be saved in the day of the Lord
and then the second one so they may learn not to blaspheme.
So it's both, they're both for the sake of repentance.
Right, you know.
They're not being thrown out of the church
and handed over to Satan.
And by the way, as we've said before,
church in the Bible has a border
and someone can be put outside it.
Yeah, but they're not being thrown out and put outside it because go pounce and we never want to see you again
Yeah, quite the opposite. It's yeah, this is our last desperate attempt to try to get you to repent
Yeah, I mean this is you know, this is sort of
The same dynamic is in place parents, right go to your room until you're ready to be with other people
Right, it's not I never want to see you again child get out, you know, it's not that it's it's okay
there's a way that we need to behave together.
So you can have to be somewhere else until you can be with the community and be in the community and live as the community.
Right now.
And and there is a similar dynamic here.
In terms of the removal, not just their individual removal to get them to repent.
But St. Paul, for example, in 1 Corinthians 5, is very clear that the fact that the people in the...
Christian community in Corinth have been not saying anything about this.
Yeah, they've been letting it go.
Have been letting it happen and some of them from what he says even sort of silently
applauding themselves for how open-minded they are about it.
Nothing like that would ever happen today.
Right.
That is actually presenting a danger to them surrounding the Eucharist.
St. John is going to say, right, that when they allow false teachers and these people to
come in and they host them at the Eucharist, that they are a stain on their love fees.
Stain, taint.
Yeah, it's harming the community to let sin go.
It's pointing to that danger.
So both for the sake of the community, if the person will not repent, they have to leave.
for the sake of the person who needs to repent.
they need to be put out as that last call for them to to repent. And in terms of the specific language
of handed over to Satan, don't miss the connection here of who's outside the camp in the wilderness,
who when you exile someone or a goat, you're sending them to a zeal. Yeah. The goat demon of the
the wilderness.
don't miss that. But implied by the fact that we want them to learn not to blaspheme,
or we want them to be saved in the day of the Lord, is the fact that reentry to the community is
possible in Christ. Repentance and restoration, right, is not only possible, but the goal.
So a final note here, a final note here, recently online.
certain circles, some people who've gotten very deeply upset about anathema.
Well, we just had the Sunday of the Triumph of Orthodoxy, so
yes, got anathema on the mind. We're depending on your Orthodox tradition and whether there was
a bishop there, you may or may not have heard some anathema.
Right, so anathema, the word means a curse.
Right?
Yeah.
Yeah, I think most literally it's like put somewhere else is what it actively means. Yeah.
But the idea is that they're under occurs. You're putting them outside the camp.
Right. If it's directed toward a person. Now there are anathemas directed toward people
from various church councils within the Orthodox tradition. More often there are teachings
right, ideas, positions, activities, actions that are declared to be anathema.
Right. And so first of all, we see that they're functioning as
threatening. Right. They're functioning as warnings to the people in the
church when they hear these things. Right. Oh, a person who teaches
XYZ, that person is anathema, that person is outside the church, right.
The
These are bad ideas. These are ideas that will be harmful to your salvation. These are things to steer clear of.
Not to do, ways not to go. They're the natural result of the other thing that church councils do,
which is a ecumenical council's at least, which is established dogma. And we've talked before about how dogma, the word originally referred to a boundary marker in property.
So you have these dogmas
that are the fences, right? The markers out at the edge of the teaching of the church,
and therefore anything that's outside of those boundary markers is de facto anathema.
And so an anathema is just the flip side of a dogma.
So if we say the truth is X, then not X by definition is outside.
side. Out of bounds is under the curse.
outside the camp, anathema, right?
But the most important thing here, so most of where things, so some of these people
who are very upset about the anathema
have a big problem with them.
Don't understand the point where I'm out to make
because they will say things.
I may or may not be referring to any person in particular. They will say things.
like, well, if you read these inathemas,
then you can see that in the past
through most of Orthodox Church history,
they thought no one outside the Orthodox Church
was saved and they were all going to hell.
Right?
But now recently, now they try to act all nice
and say that they don't think that anymore.
Right?
really what the Orthodox Church teaches.
So leaving aside the problem of, right, what do you mean by not saved and what do you mean by going to hell?
Right. Again, we've talked about those categories plenty on this show and why that's not a good way of thinking.
But there's another
Exploration. There's an actual reason for that difference, right?
between just going and reading the enathems of a council and then talking to actual Orthodox people.
the Anathomus. So we have to understand that in the Orthodox Church texts don't have authority
in and of themselves. Yeah. Well, and let me just approach that this issue from another
angle because I think it's important to show how problematic that whole methodology is.
Right?
Like, and I've seen people do this.
Like, find a good faithful Lutheran and say to him, you know, I've been reading the writings
of Martin Luther and I found this.
What do you have to say for that?
You know, because Martin Luther said some things that most modern Lutherans would definitely
reject.
We talked about it two weeks ago.
Yeah, while still calling
themselves Lutherans, and they would very rightly say to you, that's not how Lutheran
ism works.
You know, right?
So now, the writings of Martin Luther do not have the kind of canonical authority that
rulings of ecumenical councils do.
But the principle holds, which is, you can't just dig unless a religious community says
explicitly look all of our texts are basically self-applying whatever.
You can't say, look, I found this thing.
If they say that they're lying, frankly.
Yeah, but right, right.
It's not a thing.
They may be deceived themselves, but that is not a true statement.
Yeah.
You know, like, like, look, I found this thing in your, in your religious communities
past.
Ha!
Gotcha.
You know, no, that's not, that's not how it, how it works.
Yeah, it's got to be applied by someone who is
qualified or who is authorized through the position to do so. Yeah. Because texts, there's
some self-criticism here. That's part of why I want to come at it this way. Not me, well,
maybe even me personally, but within the Orthodox cap. So people don't always feel like we're
picking on them if they're not Orthodox. Since that's what we're talking about right now
with the inathemas anyway. So for us, texts don't have authority. So we aren't solo
the scriptura. Right? The bib.
The biblical text itself does not have authority.
The Holy Spirit who inspired it, guides it, transmits it,
leads the church and interpreting it as authority
because the Holy Spirit is God.
And there are particular people within the church
who have received positions of authority
to interpret and apply the scriptures.
But the text on paper doesn't have authority,
the kit.
exercise authority can't do anything. It's paper with printing on it, right?
It literally can't do anything. And the reason why this is self-critical for Orthodox
too. That's not just me taking a shot at Protestants is that we have a lot of people in the Orthodox
church. Well, I don't know if it's a lot of people. There are a lot of online Orthodox people who
speak as if they are a kind of wooden
unnew-onst Solar Scriptura Protestant, who has just added the canons and the inathemas
and certain quotes from Church Fathers to the Bible.
And treats all of those things as if they're just self-interpreting and self-applying.
The canons are not self-interpreting and self-applying anymore than the Scriptures are.
The inathemas are not self-interpreting and self-applying anymore than the Scriptures
are.
Church fathers are not self-interpreting and self-applying anymore than the Scriptures.
The Holy Spirit who stands behind them has authority as God, and there are people in the
Orthodox Church.
They're called bishops.
Let's be blunt.
They're called bishops who are interested with the authority to interpret and apply the
scriptures, the canons, the anathemas, the writings of the church fathers, and being
entrusted with that position as we've emphasized many times before on the show.
God is...
Because then their judge as to how well they live up to that calling and that authority
with which they've been entrusted in how they use it.
That's how it works in the Orthodox Church.
So back to the issue at hand.
Why does it sound different when you read the anathema's on paper versus when you talk
to an actual Orthodox Christian?
Because they're being applied in a certain way.
Let me give you an example.
example, okay, in the modern world, right, in the modern world. So if I go to average person
who identifies as a Christian, Protestant Orthodox Roman Catholic, someone who doesn't identify
as any of those doesn't matter, I go to them and I say, uh, average lay person, explain
the the Trinity to me.
Okay?
I'm going to get some kind of heresy.
Yeah.
9.9 times out of 10.
Yeah, within the first five minutes, at least one heretical thing will be said.
Yes, but so let's say just for the purpose of this example, that the person I go to, this particular person,
gives me the whole water-ice steam thing, right?
And it's basically a motorist, basically a subbellion, and the way he explains it.
Right. His explanation is motorist or subbellion.
Okay, bye.
But he just he's never studied it.
Doesn't know much about theology.
He's just got kind of a wrong-headed view of it.
Okay.
But the view he expresses when asked about the Trinity
is subbellion.
Now, let's imagine I go and I talk to someone
who is a theology professor at a oneness
pentacostal seminary.
And this professor is saying his late fifties,
He's spent
his life writing books against the doctrine of the Trinity and writing books laying out
a model that is motorist, that is rebellion. And he has had public debates with trinitarians
about it. Right. Allow me to suggest that the anathema of the Council of Nicaea against
subbellionism, applies to these two men differently.
Just obviously.
Right?
When it gets applied to the average Christian layman who's a little confused, right?
It gets applied in terms of, whoa man, that's not correct.
Let me lay out for you a better way to understand the Trinity.
Right?
whereas the person who spent his life arguing against the truth gets rebuked by that
anathema.
Rebuke to the sense that if you believe that, if you reject the doctor of dr. Dr. Dr.
Adryddi, the council of d'Iceea, you aren't properly speaking a Christian.
Yeah.
You are outside the church, right?
That's how those get applied.
And that's not being inconsistent.
That's not being wishy washy with the one person.
That's being normal, reasonable and addressing the two cases.
Never fight
I talk to that layman and I lay out a more correct way of understanding the Trinity and he
rejects it.
He says, no, I don't believe that.
And he doubles down with the modalism.
It says, no, this is what I think is true.
He starts moving over into the other category.
Right?
If he goes, it starts talking to his friends and trying to form a faction in his church,
he's moving way over into that other category.
Rebuke.
Right? And so the Orthodox Church, when it's addressing people who have grown up with
no knowledge of the Orthodox Church in its teachings, right? They're not going to apply
the Anathemas to those people in the same way that they apply them to someone who understood
those teachings full well and rejected them. Those are two different scenarios.
So...
just to choose a random example, because of course, this is not directed at any particular
person. The second council of Dicea, the seventh
ecu medical council, the Anathomas, it gets those who refuse to venerate icons.
The Types, those Anathomas were spoken historically. They were spoken to people who had been
murdering imprisoning, torturing people for owning icons.
And smashing them and piece, smashing the icons of pieces of burning.
them throwing them into the ocean, etc.
Yes. Right. And so yeah, they get rebuked in pretty harsh terms. Okay. Now we have an
average evangelical Protestant trying to follow Christ as best they know how. They walk into
an Orthodox church one day. They see people kissing an icon that gives them the heebie
GPs so they say, you know, I don't think that's right. That seems weird.
Okay, those anathema's do not apply to the second person the same way they apply to the first person
Yeah, and that is not being wishy washy that's being normal
being sensible and reasonable
Right they are applied differently in these different cases because they're different people and because what's the goal?
The goal is not to identify good guys and bad guys. It's not to identify an in-group and an out group
The goal is to call people who are on the wrong path or who have wrong ideas to repentance.
And if the best way to bring someone to the right point of view is to come and speak
to them lovingly and explain and teach them what we believe to be true, that's what we're
going to do.
If a person is hardened and argumentative, right?
And opposing the truth, then we're going to try for review to bring them to repentance.
which I mean like this is actually baked
This is actually baked into the very text of these anathema, right?
Because it's the phrase those who teach exist in most of them, you know, to those who teach
or those who say X, Y, and Z, not to those who think or to those who speculate or to those
who don't know any better.
Don't know any better.
It's those who teach, right?
who teach this heresy anathema.
There?
Yeah.
All right.
Well, this didn't go quite as late as the question were not done yet, but this didn't
go quite as late as I thought it would.
But nonetheless, we have some closing thoughts.
Well number one, this will certainly not be the end of our discussion of Torah in the
church and how to apply it.
We will come back to that.
next time, actually we're planning to do an all
live Q&A, so you know, jam up those phone lines and make Montesca Trudy earn her living.
I see already very ably does. But I just wanted to summarize some of my own thoughts from this
episode and also a little bit from the last one talking about Torah and how it applies for Christians.
And the entry point for some of my thoughts is we got an email within the past few days actually.
And we're someone who wrote.
us. And the situation was that he was doing something that was under the direction of his spiritual
father and in my own assessment, pretty normal thing to do. But was explicitly being rejected by
by people he was running to on the internet.
And he was concerned, like, well, looked...
there's cannons that seem to be relevant to this and my spiritual father is applying this
one way.
But this is what the cannons say and whatever it might be.
And the question that I had and I wrote him back and I said, well, he said in his email,
he said, I'm concerned I might be under anathema.
And the question I said to him was, well, who exactly is going to anathmatize you?
Right?
one.
on Twitter or on a discord server somewhere,
or are they going to, like, if so, who cares, right?
Who cares?
Because as we said, there are people
who actually have authority to pronounce anathemas.
And it's not me, right?
It's not the interwebs.
They're
are people who actually have this authority.
And as Father Stephen said,
it's funny, Americans are like,
but what if a bishop is wrong?
God will hold that person accountable.
Like he will.
He will.
Don't we believe that God is active
and here in doing stuff?
We do.
God will hold the account,
they are accountable to God,
not to me personally, right?
not to
mobs on Twitter or wherever else. So why is this important? Well, it's not just to re-emphasize
the point we made earlier about who has the authority to do these things, but it is actually about
this question of who we are. What is our identity? Right? And this is one of the big questions of Torah.
What is the identity of Israel?
And therefore, what is the identity of the church?
The renewed Israel.
And I think based on some of the questions we've got, which, they've been great questions
people, so please don't feel in any way embarrassed by asking them.
There've been great questions.
Some of them have been tough.
Some of them have, they sent me, you know, to the books, probably not for Stephen, but
definitely me on several occasions.
You know, to try to understand these things better myself.
Thanks for watching.
I'll see you guys next time.
I think from a lot of the questions that one of the ways that we tend to try to understand
and to digest this question of the Torah and of the scriptures in general, of all kinds
of elements of church tradition that we can point to, right?
We've got some church.
If we don't have this pure
intergal text or protection
or a flood of sections for
biological detector means
that the
to analyze these in ways that in some ways somehow don't assume that it's actually happening
within community. Right? And that's the question of the email, you know, I'm scared I might be
under anathema. Even while he's being obedient within his community, to the person that God gave him,
his own spiritual father. And why is this?
a problem. Well, I think that it is a problem because as we said earlier, what it means
to be a Christian is bound up in community. It is not something one does individually.
Yes, I as a person need to make choices about how to live my life. I am the one who is
in charge of this being who is me.
me, but it is not something that I do individually. It is something I do in my community, right?
In obedience to my own spiritual father, my own bishop, in concert with the other people
in my actual, on the ground parish community. This is one of the big points that we make
all the time in this podcast, but we're applying it in a particular way this time, but it's
not separable from community. And even the
idea of being cut off from among the people. There's a sense in which being truly cut off from
the church, especially if it becomes like long-term, that's not a Christian out there anymore.
Let's say come back and be Christian, yet to be part of the family, yet to be part of the family.
You can't be cut off from life and be alive. Right? You can't. And I think that a lot of this problem
get exacerbated.
in the age of social media.
And I say this as a participant in social media.
You know, a lot of the work that I do is in social media,
but that's not the only reason that I'm on social media.
I'm using it for myself.
I'm staying in touch with family and friends
and reading things and being informed
and learning about stuff and whatever.
But because of the way that social media works, right?
Like it's data that comes at us, largely visual,
but there's also sometimes audio and whatever.
It's data that comes out of us.
And so we receive it as data.
We process it as data.
And it's mostly an individual experience.
Now, there are, I know there's other people
on the other end, like I was chatting with people
on the YouTube chat this evening and so forth.
I see you, I see you're out there.
But nonetheless, we're not in each other's presence.
So there's a significant limit that's happening there.
And so it's easier for me, right?
I see you as just words on the page.
See?
easier for me to just analyze it, analyze you as words. I know that you're not just words,
but that's easy. That's how all of us are doing this, right? And so what happens then is
we are not on purpose, I think, but let's be on guard, okay? We're nurturing a kind of
virtual Christianity. And that in that virtual Christianity, canons do things like apply
themselves because it's
just text anyway, right? Right? You know, the Bible applies itself. It's all just text anyway.
It's when we're actually in each other's presence and praying together and worshiping together
and having to be obedient to the person who is leading our community. That's Christianity.
This is so explicit everywhere in the scriptures and it's
just baked into what the church is.
And there is a kind of million man's schism
that is happening when we dissociate ourselves
from the community and attempt to become a thing
called Orthodox Christian in a way that's utterly individualized.
Like, I have seen people online, and I'm not joking about this.
I've seen people online that calling themselves Orthodox Christians,
calling themselves sometimes Catecuments,
Which is a very-
specific category, right, as is Orthodox Christian, but a Catechumin is a very specific category.
And some of these people have literally never been to an Orthodox church or they don't
go very often or they, you know, and I've seen them say that.
I saw someone once say, I'm a Catechumin, although I still haven't visited my local parish.
I'm like, well, how did you become a Catech?
What?
It gets not a thing.
But when you had this kind of virtual Christianity, it is a thing.
It's not.
actually a thing. It's not. It's just an idea. It's a concept. And it functions because people
give it, people use their agency to give it functionality, but it doesn't actually exist.
It doesn't actually exist. It's like saying I'm married, but where is your husband? Where's your
wife? Is that a person somewhere? Or like, I'm a parent. Okay, show me your children.
It's not a thing you can do.
without that. And one of my big takeaways, this is my biggest takeaway, I think. My biggest
takeaway from talking about the Torah and the way that it functions within the church is that it
functions within the church. We made this point last time, which is you do not need to reinvent the
wheel. Right. And so so I understand why someone might ask a question like, well, okay, I see this
on the Torah but
But are we doing that?
You know, shouldn't we be doing X, Y, and Z?
I understand why people ask that close questions.
And it's fine. It's fine. Ask them, you know.
But, but, but, ideally we get to the point where we say,
okay, I see this in the Torah, I don't understand how that's being applied in the church,
or if it is, or whatever.
Let me dive more deeply into the tradition of the church and try to understand
and
how the church has digested this and not assume that the church hasn't.
Because if I think like, oh, I spotted something that the church has been missing all this
time, I'm wrong.
This is true of the scriptures.
It's true of the church councils.
Like like a lot of people were unhappy at us when several episodes ago we rejected universalism,
you know, rather like the ecumenical councils do.
think about this okay like you're gonna
embrace whatever form we've been universalism and you're going to say okay these church councils
got this wrong and for the last over thousand years the church has gotten it wrong.
Then that's not orthodox Christianity that's something else something else right that's essentially
saying I know and the community of the church doesn't or I'm right and the church has been wrong
the Holy Spirit has not successfully guided
the church all of this time. I got it. I got it. Right. And so the way that the Torah and all
the scriptures function within the church is within the church. It's not arbitrary. It's not
that the, you know, the bishops can say whatever the heck they want. They are constrained, but not by a
text. They're constrained by the Holy Spirit, who is guiding the church together. And no, that
that doesn't work out kind of.
mathematically. Like there's not a method of formula that you can apply where like, oh,
if I apply this formula, I'll always get the correct answer. It's not how it works. And
the biggest reason that it doesn't work that way is because I am not omniscient and I am
not sinless and I am not omnipotent. And so therefore I have to have some humility and
to understand what's
in the Torah more thoroughly is one of the ways of pursuing that humility and seeing how
it's applied in the church.
Okay, rant over.
Father Stephen, it's your turn.
I'm going to be somewhat nicer to our internet friends.
I mean, not a lot.
I'm not a nice person, but a little.
Um, yeah, I want to.
I want to talk a little bit about zeal.
Zeal is not a bad thing.
According to the scriptures, it's a good thing.
Right, it's a good thing.
The big example, Biblically of zeal, is of course, in the Torah, is
Phineas.
Right, who?
and say, uh, and so plague.
but all poor by skewering an Israelite man in the person with whom he was chambering.
Fuse of phrase that was in our epistle book last week.
There's a euphemism.
And for this act of frankly violence, right?
He and his descendants were awarded the High Priesthood in Israel.
the
that he had was not a zeal for violence or a lust for blood, right? That's not
being what's being praised here. The zeal is for the purity of the camp. The
purity of God's people, maintaining that purity. And there are a number of other
figures who we can talk about running through the scriptures, who manifest
that kind of zeal.
for the purity of God's people and the purity of the camp.
And when I look at folks on the inner webs, right, or the ox folks on the inner webs,
other Christian folks on the inner webs, I see that there are a lot of people with zeal,
specifically that kind of zeal.
Zeal for the purity of God's people, for the purity of the church, right.
We can't have these people teaching these things that are wrong.
We can't have these
people who want to change things about the church based on the zeitgeist, right? The spirit
of the age is a demon, right? We can't have this. These people need to be opposed at every
turn. They need to be rebuked. We need to fight back against them, seal, right? And again,
necessarily a bad thing. But we also have to remember St. Paul.
Because Saul of Tarsus in his early years as a radical had a lot of zeal.
And he had exactly that kind of zeal, zeal for the purity of God's people.
That's why he became a Pharisee.
But that zeal kind of got out of control for St. Paul.
what started out as...
I must be pure. The people must be pure. This is how we will receive God's blessings.
Turned into a kind of violence and a kind of persecution that led to him all
of a sudden persecuting Christians. That led to him standing by in a proving of the murder of
of Saint Stephen.
Things got out of control.
Later St. Paul would say he had zeal but not according to knowledge.
That brings us to 1 Corinthians 5 that we read a verse from just a little bit ago.
He's got this problem with the church in Corinth, with this fellow we mentioned, who's engaged
sexual immorality. Unrepent. And no
in the community seems to care. Want to say anything, let alone do anything about it. Some of them,
as we said, even congratulating themselves for how wise and open-minded they were. And so St. Paul,
in part, in that letter has to upgrade them, has to rebuke them for lacking zeal,
for not having zeal for the purity of their community and their church,
for letting this
This unrepentant sin continued to stain their gatherings.
But there's a difference.
There's a difference when you read everything he says to the church in Corinth.
There's another piece.
St. Paul now has some knowledge.
St. Paul is a wiser man.
He's able to keep a couple of different thoughts in his head at the same time.
One of those is still that seal.
The purity of the church must be maintained.
But the other piece is this unrepentant sinner needs to repent.
That purifying the church doesn't mean driving this guy away for the sake of driving him away,
declaring him unfit, ridiculing him.
So, he's got some kind of violence against him, some kind of retribution.
It means trying to bring him to repentance.
We could do that with a conversation great.
It takes a rebuke.
That's what we have to do.
If we have to excommunicate him publicly, that's what we have to do.
Whatever we have to do to, as April says, save this man's spirit, save his soul on the
day when Christ...
judges, all of us. That's what we have to do in order to purify the church and keep the
church pure. He can hold those two things together. And so to all those people who I just
commended on their zeal on the internet, I have to say also the other piece. We have to
keep this other peace in mind.
That person who day after day identifies as a Orthodox Christian and post things that are
not in keeping or are the opposite of Orthodox Christian teaching.
Maybe smug about it.
That's a person God loves.
That's a person for whom Christ died.
That's a person who you need to purify the church from by bringing them to repentance.
I'm sorry guys.
and you're mostly guys. Not everyone needs to be rebuked all the time.
Right? Not everyone needs to be rebuked all the time. A lot of people need to be educated. A lot of
people need to be brought along. A lot of people need to have some kind of connection with somebody
where they feel like the person actually cares about them and then they'll be able to hear what they
have to say and be critical.
corrected. Some people need to be corrected privately. Some people need to be corrected publicly.
We need to exercise some wisdom and some knowledge about this. We need to keep the goal in mind.
Is how I'm talking to this person and how I'm talking about this person? Is this going to
achieve the result that I should want of trying to bring them to repentance and restoration?
I'm trying to get them to embrace the fullness of the Orthodox faith.
Right? Or is what I am saying going to get me congratulated by my friends for how well
I own them and destroyed them with fax and logic? So one of those is pride. And the other
one is trying to save someone's soul, which St. Peter tells us will cover a multitude of
our own sins. That said to all the folks out there who have people in mind
who they think I'm talking to and are saying, yeah, get them.
Sometimes people do need to be rebuked.
Right?
Like in Corinth.
Sometimes we can't just all get along.
Sometimes we can't, almost never can we just overlook
this stuff.
We need to be wise about how we handle it,
but sometimes the way it has to be handled is a rebuk,
a public rebuk.
Right?
Sometimes that is what has to be done.
And we do need people with a little bit of zeal and some courage to do that.
And people who have the wisdom to know how to do even that, how to issue a rebuke in a way
that might bring someone to repentance.
So hopefully, right, if you haven't...
Left social media permanently as I think we all should or at least left it for Len which in
Arguably everyone should if you're still on it right now
Let me be a time to have some serious thoughts about this, right? So not about dampening anybody's zeal
It's not about telling people they shouldn't care about the purity of the church
It's about also being wise and being smart and keeping the goal in mind
Right.
God desires that no man should perish, but that they should turn and live.
That has to be our goal too. He promises us blessings for anyone who can bring someone who
airs someone who sins, someone who has gone astray back into the fold. That's what we should be
pursuing. Not our egos, right? Definitely not money. Right? In these interactions.
and that's what we should be after.
Amen.
All right, well that is our show for tonight.
Thank you very much, all of you for listening.
If you didn't get through to us live,
we'd still like to hear from you.
Next time it's gonna be an all-live Q&A,
so make sure you show up for that.
You can email us also though at LordOfSpirits.nation.
faith.com, you can message us at our Facebook page.
You can leave us a voice mail at speakpipe.com slash LordOfSpirits.
And you feel of basic questions about Orthodox...
or you need to help finding a parish, head over to Orthodoxintro.org.
And join us for our live broadcast on the second and fourth Thursdays of the month at 7 p.m. Eastern 4 p.m. Pacific.
I've been planning out all that I'd say to you since you slipped away.
Know that I still remain true. I've been wishing out the days.
If you are on Facebook as father, Stephen has not.
Follow our page, join our discussion group, leave reviews and ratings in all the appropriate places.
But most importantly, share this show with one of your friends who is going to benefit from it.
And finally, be sure to go to www.extrafaith.com.
Support and help make sure we and lots of other AFR
podcasters stay on the air.
Please say that if you hadn't of gone now,
I wouldn't have lost you another way from wherever you are.
Come back.
Thank you, good night.
God bless you.
You've been listening to the Lord of Spirits
with Orthodox Christian priests, father Andrew Stephen
Damick and father Stephen DeYoung,
a listener-supported presentation of ancient faith radio.
And I be held.
and I heard the voice of many angels round about the throne and the beasts and the elders
and the number of them was 10,000 times 10,000 than thousands of thousands
seeing with a loud voice worthy as the land that was slain to receive power and
riches and wisdom and strength and honor and glory and blessing.
Revelation chapter 5 verses 11 through 12.
Glory to Jesus Christ, glory forever, you're listening to ancient faithradio.com.
Jesus' last words to His disciples were go and make disciples of all the nations.
Unfortunately, many parishes are struggling to follow this commandment in reclaiming the
the Great Commission.